<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog</id>
    <title>MeteoScientific Blog</title>
    <updated>2030-01-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog"/>
    <subtitle>MeteoScientific Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/metsci_pro_favicon.svg</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Read This First]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/welcome</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/welcome"/>
        <updated>2030-01-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[LoRaWAN sensors on Helium can be used for an awful lot of things, and in this blog we use AI (plus Nik at MetSci) to write about exploring some of the possible use cases.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>LoRaWAN sensors on <a href="https://www.helium.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Helium</a> can be used for an awful lot of things, and in this blog we use AI (plus Nik at MetSci) to write about exploring some of the possible use cases.</p>
<p>If this is your first time at the MetSci (short for MeteoScientific) site and you just want to try using things and muddling through, head over to the <a href="https://console.meteoscientific.com/front/login" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Console</a>, sign up for an account and get going.</p>
<p>If you'd like step-by-step instructions on how to get started, check out our <a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/docs/tutorial-basics/intro-to-console">Tutorials</a>.
Oh, you actually want to read the blog, and you'd like to know a little more?  Cool!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="author-stuff">Author Stuff<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/welcome#author-stuff" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Author Stuff" title="Direct link to Author Stuff">​</a></h2>
<p>If you see that an author is just MetSci, you're reading a guided LLM piece.  If the author is <strong>also</strong> Nik, you know there was some human redacting.  If it's <strong>only</strong> Nik, it's a fully human-written piece.</p>
<p>You should consider this blog a general exploration of using the Helium LoRaWAN, not an exhaustive resource for every possible application.  Go get 'em, tigers!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="welcome" term="welcome"/>
        <category label="pinned" term="pinned"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is One Sensor Enough?]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled"/>
        <updated>2025-06-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[How a single IoT sensor can turn your neighborhood into a playground and get people interested in IoT, featuring a heavy metal sled, LoRaWAN tracking, and community building.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What if I told you that a single IoT sensor (yep, just one) could turn your entire neighborhood into a playground that got people interested in IoT?</p>
<p>There's this story in IoT that you need thousands of sensors to make a difference.  Maybe that's true.  </p>
<p>Today I wanted to talk about what you can do with just one sensor.  Before we begin with that, I should give you some context.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="action--iot">ACTION &amp; IoT<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#action--iot" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ACTION &amp; IoT" title="Direct link to ACTION &amp; IoT">​</a></h2>
<p>For as far back as I can remember, I've been active.  Running, swimming, wrestling, lacrosse, and just being out in the wild moving through terrain.  Action has been the great restorative for me, both a source of daily joy and a catch net for times of depression.</p>
<p>We are the same in that way, you and I, because we are human.  Humans feel better when they move, when they physically work.  It's in our genes.  A bias for (thinking) action is part of what has made us the dominant species on the planet.</p>
<p>Over the past few years as I've gotten deeper into IoT, I have set aside much of my old action.  I call it "glueing my face to the computer", and while it has been intensely fascinating to dive into the world of IoT and LoRa and uplinks and routing, it has not been good for action.</p>
<p>In fact, with a few rare exceptions, like this helicopter delivery of a weather station to a mountain top:</p>
<video controls="" preload="metadata" poster="/img/blog/video-thumbnails/weather-station-delivery-thumb.png" style="width:100%;max-width:800px;margin:20px auto;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15);background-color:var(--metsci-white)"><source src="https://video.meteoscientific.com/helicopter-delivery-of-iot-weather-station-el-cajon-mtn.mp4" type="video/mp4"><p>Your browser does not support the video tag.</p></video>
<p>or hiking in a giant 915 MHz antenna and half the accoutrements of a LoRaWAN gateway in a 70 lb pack on that same mountain range:</p>
<video controls="" preload="metadata" poster="/img/blog/video-thumbnails/giant-antenna-delivery-thumb.png" style="width:100%;max-width:800px;margin:20px auto;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15);background-color:var(--metsci-white)"><source src="https://video.meteoscientific.com/hiking-in-giant-lorawan-915-antenna.mp4" type="video/mp4"><p>Your browser does not support the video tag.</p></video>
<p>IoT and real world human action seldom overlap.  One of the main selling points of IoT is that you actually do less action.  With a network of sensors, you can focus down to only doing the action that matters.</p>
<p>In one sense that's much more efficient, and certainly better for a business.  In the other, that brings us closer to death.  I'm not ready to die yet, and so I sought a way to increase action with two caveats:</p>
<p>First, I would do it with others.  I'm no misanthrope, and while I've had plenty of joyous times alone, there's something genetically satisfying about sharing physical effort with someone else.  It's (part) of what makes sex satisfying, but the joy of joint work is not solely the realm of procreation.</p>
<p>A hard run with a friend, or a climb out of a deep canyon, or crossing a river, or just lifting weights with a group all trigger deep centers of joy.  We evolved to work together; it's how we brought down mammoths, kept the children safe, maintained and grew the tribe.</p>
<p>Together is how we best operate.</p>
<p>Second, I would involve IoT.  I love this tech; I think it's so cool the way we can start to measure the world, record it, and react to the world much faster, more accurately, and over far longer range than ever we could before.  IoT is so clearly the way forward for the way humans sense the world that ignoring it borders on the criminal.</p>
<p>Still, IoT is a dense thicket.  To use it you typically have to be able to do more than just make text bold or italic; there's code involved, hardware, software, connectivity, and more.  In fact, the deeper you get into IoT, the more that is required you know just to get something simple to work.</p>
<p>How then can we integrate the joy of action together with the barriers of getting something to actually work that surround IoT?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="beginnings">BEGINNINGS<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#beginnings" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to BEGINNINGS" title="Direct link to BEGINNINGS">​</a></h2>
<p>Years ago, when I was deep in my metal working phase, a buddy of mine came by to give me a couple of heavy iron elongated pyramids that looked like teeth off a robot T-rex.</p>
<div style="display:flex;justify-content:center;margin:20px auto"><img src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/blog/2025-06-22-single-iot-sensor-power-the-sled/dredger_teeth.JPG" alt="Heavy iron dredger teeth from San Diego bay dredger, looking like robot T-rex teeth" style="max-width:800px;width:100%;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15)"></div>
<p>In actual fact they were the worn out teeth of the San Diego bay dredger, the thing that digs out the bottom of the bay so it's deep enough for our various and sundry aircraft carriers, destroyers, and other large ships that dock here in America's Finest city and make up much of the US Pacific fleet.</p>
<p>For the longest time I didn't know what to do with 'em.  Then one day on the internet back in 2015-ish, I saw some football guys pushing a metal sled.</p>
<p>Ah, I thought, those dredger teeth would make excellent sled feet, and I could weld together my own heavy metal sled out of scrap I had laying around that I could push around the neighborhood causing all kinds of grinding-steel-on-concrete noise and generally be very pleased with myself as I bulldogged the thing around the block.</p>
<p>So I did.  I used it a few times because I love action, but other actions called in both real and virtual worlds, and the sled sat next to the weight rack until last Thursday.</p>
<p>Through a longer turn of events, I ended up pushing the sled to a buddy's house about ½ a mile away as a workout and a challenge for him to push back.</p>
<p>He did, and as I heard it grinding towards me on the street it hit me that I should share this idea, of pushing the sled between houses in a neighborhood, in a way that combined my love of action with my love of IoT, and the rapidly growing capabilities of vibe-coding (which just means working with AI to build something).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="coordination">COORDINATION<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#coordination" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to COORDINATION" title="Direct link to COORDINATION">​</a></h2>
<p>So over the weekend I built a website to coordinate IoT action amongst strangers.</p>
<p>It relies on the IoT device of a Digital Matter Oyster2, which is a slightly older piece of tech that is enormously stable and delivers on all the promises of IoT &amp; LoRaWAN; long battery life, long communication range, and dead simple to use.</p>
<div style="display:flex;justify-content:center;margin:20px auto"><img src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/blog/2025-06-22-single-iot-sensor-power-the-sled/oyster2-tracker-on-helium.JPG" alt="Digital Matter Oyster2 IoT tracker device with Helium branding" style="max-width:800px;width:100%;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15)"></div>
<p>The Oyster is attached to the sled.  We added a wheels option so you can make it easier if needed, but most of the time the wheels are just mounted on that pin on the back.</p>
<div style="display:flex;justify-content:center;margin:20px auto"><img src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/blog/2025-06-22-single-iot-sensor-power-the-sled/sled-with-tracker.jpg" alt="The sled on delivery with the Oyster2 tracker mounted" style="max-width:800px;width:100%;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15)"></div>
<p>When the sled is stationary for more than 7 minutes, the Oyster goes to sleep for 24 hours.  When the sled is moving, an accelerometer in the Oyster wakes the device up and it starts transmitting every 20 seconds.</p>
<video controls="" preload="metadata" poster="/img/blog/video-thumbnails/get-after-it-sled-pushing-thumb.png" style="width:100%;max-width:800px;margin:20px auto;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15);background-color:var(--metsci-white)"><source src="https://video.meteoscientific.com/sled-pushing-nik.mp4" type="video/mp4"><p>Your browser does not support the video tag.</p></video>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nerd-talk">Nerd Talk<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#nerd-talk" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nerd Talk" title="Direct link to Nerd Talk">​</a></h2>
<p>The Oyster sends data packets via uplinks through the Helium Network to a LoRaWAN Network Server, or LNS.  In this case, we're using the MeteoScientific LNS Console.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://console.meteoscientific.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MetSci Console</a> is available for anyone to use, just sign up.  I've written a whole series of <a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/docs/tutorial-basics/LoRaWAN-Big-Picture">Tutorials</a> on how to use it if you need help.  You get your first 400 data packets for free, and after they they cost $.0001 each.  Yeah, pretty cheap.</p>
<p>The LNS decodes the packets and sends them on via an http integration to a Cloudflare Worker.</p>
<p>The Worker puts the incoming packets from the Oyster into a Cloudflare D1 database.  It then reads that database and updates the website that coordinates and informs all the human actions.</p>
<div style="display:flex;justify-content:center;margin:20px auto"><img src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/blog/2025-06-22-single-iot-sensor-power-the-sled/cloudflare-worker-bindings.png" alt="Cloudflare Worker bindings showing connections to Assets, R2 bucket, D1 database, and KV namespace for intersections" style="max-width:600px;width:100%;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15)"></div>
<p>As I've said, Action is one of my loves.</p>
<p>You can go to the website to see how the rest of it works, but before I send you there, let me walk you through the general workflow.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-real-world">The Real World<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#the-real-world" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Real World" title="Direct link to The Real World">​</a></h2>
<p>Let's say you're a reasonably fit person out walking your dog.  If, like me, you want to work out with other people but joining a gym isn't your thing, you might be interested in a flyer you see on a telephone pole that says "Hard Work - Sled Pushing"</p>
<div style="display:flex;justify-content:center;margin:20px auto"><img src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/blog/2025-06-22-single-iot-sensor-power-the-sled/sled-pushing-flyer.JPG" alt="Flyer for sled pushing signup in Normal Heights, San Diego California" style="max-width:600px;width:100%;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15)"></div>
<p>You tear off one of the tabs at the bottom which has a QR code and 5 or 6 character password and take it home.</p>
<p>You scan the QR code and find the site, read through the description, and decide to sign up.</p>
<p>The very short version of the description is that you're signing up for a heavy metal sled to be pushed to you by a stranger, then you're responsible for "delivering" (by pushing) the sled to the next stranger.</p>
<p>The distances are bounded by 300 and 1,000 meters so that the push will be neither too long nor short, and the general rules (during the day, of course you can bring a friend, contact me if anything goes wrong) are laid out.</p>
<p>When you sign up, you enter your email, the handle you want to go by publicly, your address, and the password you entered.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-quick-revisit-of-nerdville">A Quick Revisit of Nerdville<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#a-quick-revisit-of-nerdville" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A Quick Revisit of Nerdville" title="Direct link to A Quick Revisit of Nerdville">​</a></h3>
<p>The Cloudflare Worker receives that information and uses the Haversine formula to calculate both your address latitude and longitude.  It then runs your coordinates through a Cloudflare KV pair of every intersection in the neighborhood so it can give others a general idea of where you are without giving away your address (i.e. "Nik near 35th and Copley just signed up").</p>
<p>The Worker puts all that data into a Cloudflare D1 table.  Once you're in the table, the Worker figures out where you should go in the sled delivery queue.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-feedback-loop">The Feedback Loop<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#the-feedback-loop" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Feedback Loop" title="Direct link to The Feedback Loop">​</a></h2>
<p>You can see where you are in the queue on the website, and when the pusher before you starts their push (calculated by the Oyster recording movement outside of a 15 meter radius from the pusher's address), the Worker fires off an email via Mailgun telling you the sled is coming.</p>
<p>When the sled enters the 15 meter radius around your address, you'll get another email confirming that the sled has been dropped off and giving you the address of where you'll push to.</p>
<p>This continues on for as long as people sign up; at the end of the queue it just loops back to the beginning.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="making-the-map">Making The Map<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#making-the-map" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Making The Map" title="Direct link to Making The Map">​</a></h2>
<p>All of this information about location is displayed on a PMTiles map I generated after downlaading an 80GB map of the entire world and processing out just my little neighborhood using a local machine I call Monstra for the processing (3 x 4070 Super Ti GPUs and a Threadripper).</p>
<div style="display:flex;justify-content:center;margin:20px auto"><img src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/blog/2025-06-22-single-iot-sensor-power-the-sled/monstra-gpu-and-threadripper-local-ai.jpg" alt="Triple GPU machine with Threadripper for running local LLM and AI tasks" style="max-width:600px;width:100%;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15)"></div>
<p>The PMTiles map is stored in a Cloudflare R2 and displayed on the site, with the live tracker of the sled on it:</p>
<div style="display:flex;justify-content:center;margin:20px auto"><img src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/img/blog/2025-06-22-single-iot-sensor-power-the-sled/sled-tracking-map.png" alt="The displayed PMTiles map I built with Monstra" style="max-width:600px;width:100%;border-radius:8px;border:4px solid var(--metsci-primary);box-shadow:0 4px 12px rgba(217, 74, 24, 0.15)"></div>
<p>So that's the combination of nerd workflow and action.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-next-steps">The Next Steps<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#the-next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Next Steps" title="Direct link to The Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<p>If you're in our little neighborhood of Normal Heights, you can <a href="https://sled.meteoscientific.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sign up to have the sled "delivered" to you</a>, and then you'll be on the hook to deliver it to the next person.
&nbsp;
As more people sign up, we get two very important things.</p>
<p>First, we combine IoT and Action, which is a source of deep joy for me.  Every person that participates is using IoT, and many of them will learn just a little bit more about how they're using it just from interacting with the sled website.  I try to answer their questions up front in the <a href="https://sled.meteoscientific.com/faq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sled FAQ section</a>) on the sled site; that way they're not afraid to ask.</p>
<p>Second, I get to connect with the section of all the people in my neighborhood (about 5,000 families total according to US Census statistic) who are willing to engage in a string of hot and sweaty deliveries from and to a stranger.  I've got the feeling they'll be my kind of people.</p>
<p>There is one other aspect of this one-sensor project that's pretty cool; this system is repeatable and cheap.</p>
<p>It runs entirely on the free tiers of Cloudflare Workers, D1, R2, and KV. It's all in a Github repo that I'd be happy to share, though I'll warn you that the Worker is messy and for now, it'll be a bit than just "copy/paste" to get it going.</p>
<p>The only cost is the tracking device.  The Oyster2 is (generally) no longer sold, but you can get the next gen Oyster3 that runs about $130.  I'd recommend getting one from <a href="https://www.lonestartracking.com/tracking-devices/oyster-lora-gps-tracking-device-915mhz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LoneStar Tracking</a>.  That's where I got my Oyster, and Tommy at LoneStar is good people.</p>
<p>You could get creative here and find a device that gathers more than just GPS data; say, air quality, or temperature, etc. and display that as well.</p>
<p>You may have read this and thought this is all too much, and there's some aspect of it that you just couldn't do.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="yes-you-can">Yes, You Can<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/06/22/Single-IoT-Sensor-Power-The-Sled#yes-you-can" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Yes, You Can" title="Direct link to Yes, You Can">​</a></h2>
<p>If you've read this far, you absolutely have the two critical things required to make a project work; the <strong>focus to read</strong> and the <strong>curiosity to keep going</strong>.  Everything else is just action, and humans are built for action!</p>
<p>Those two things are all anyone needs to succeed in the world of IoT, which is, after all, the thing that will change our world.</p>
<p>With those two things and one sensor, you too can expand a new truth about IoT.</p>
<p>What'll your one-sensor project be?</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>Author</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p><strong>Nik Hawks</strong> is a LoRaWAN Educator &amp; Builder at <a href="https://meteoscientific.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MeteoScientific</a>. He writes to educate and delight people considering IoT, and to inspire other IoT nerds to build and deploy their own projects into the world. He runs a <a href="https://pod.metsci.show/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcast</a> discussing all things LoRaWAN and is psyched to hear about what you're building, whether it's a one sensor playground or a million sensor rollout.</p></div></div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="business" term="business"/>
        <category label="helium" term="helium"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Four Ways To Improve Your LoRaWAN Business]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/30/4-Ways-To-Improve-Your-LoRaWAN-Business</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/30/4-Ways-To-Improve-Your-LoRaWAN-Business"/>
        <updated>2025-04-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The number one threat to LoRaWAN isn’t technical issues or competition, according to Alper Yegin, CEO of the LoRa Alliance.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The number one threat to LoRaWAN isn’t technical issues or competition, according to Alper Yegin, CEO of the <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LoRa Alliance</a>.</p>
<p>It’s <strong>awareness</strong>.  Not enough people know about LPWANs, let alone LoRaWAN.  What does that mean for you, the business owner who is deploying LoRaWAN to service clients?</p>
<p><em>This is for anyone exploring or deploying LoRaWAN as part of a business solution—whether you’re an integrator building out a product, a founder launching a sensor-powered service, or a company exploring IoT for compliance, energy savings, or smarter operations.</em></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="start-with-a-problem">Start With A Problem<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/30/4-Ways-To-Improve-Your-LoRaWAN-Business#start-with-a-problem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Start With A Problem" title="Direct link to Start With A Problem">​</a></h3>
<p>As Rish Chauhan, head of Business Development at <a href="https://www.thethingsnetwork.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TTN</a> says, you have to “start with a problem.”</p>
<p>It’s not magic; that’s the whole purpose of a business: To solve somebody else’s problems.</p>
<p>People buy cars to solve the problem of getting to work or the grocery store or the gym.  They don’t need to know how an alternator works, or whether or not there’s an M20B25 or 27 engine in a 1979 BMW 320i.  The car gets them to work; they don’t care exactly how it does it.</p>
<p>That’s something those of us in the LoRaWAN world can forget.  We spend a lot of time geeking out on the fascinating tech of it, but as Andy Humphrey over at <a href="https://harmonyanalytica.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Harmony Analytica</a> says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What the customer wants is what matters. You're serving the customer, not your tech desires.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Once you’ve solved their problem, THEN you can start talking about how you solved it, and let that lead into solving even more problems.  This is Humphrey’s <strong>land and expand</strong> strategy, where you land with one solution, then start going sideways to introduce more sensor types.</p>
<p>Now, that doesn’t mean you have to  start with just one sensor.  Bansi at the firm <a href="https://www.macnman.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Macnman</a> recommends starting with at least 100 sensors as the sweet spot for getting enough data and justifying the infrastructure cost.  <a href="https://pod.metsci.show/episode/from-handfuls-to-hundreds-bansi-talks-scale" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">In his podcast episode</a> he gives the smoke detector example.</p>
<p>Think of how much you can cover with one LoRaWAN enabled smoke detector in a ten story building vs multiple LoRaWAN smoke alarms on each floor.  One is cute, the other saves lives and machinery.</p>
<p>Starting focused doesn’t necessarily mean to start small.</p>
<p>Finally, you may not know what problems they have when you go in; maybe you're walking in cold, or you just bumped into someone at the coffee shop.  <a href="https://www.senseability.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Scott Andrews</a>, whose LoRaWAN work spans both the public and private sector advises you to just ask:  "Ask about their machines and what they do and how they work."</p>
<p>Awareness may be the number one threat facing LoRaWAN, but in the course of the 15 conversations I’ve had in the past few weeks starting up <a href="https://pod.metsci.show/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Business of LoRaWAN podcast</a>, the business side faces other challenges, among them how complicated it can be for non-engineers to use.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="make-it-easy">Make It Easy<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/30/4-Ways-To-Improve-Your-LoRaWAN-Business#make-it-easy" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Make It Easy" title="Direct link to Make It Easy">​</a></h3>
<p>This is the difference between encouraging small business owners to deploy their own networks and coming in as a full stack integrator; one has the problem but struggles with the solution.  The other has the solution and needs to find the problem.</p>
<p>One happy middle ground is to make using LoRaWAN a lot easier by designing for beginners.</p>
<p>That’s what Slaven Damjanovic at <a href="https://glamos.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GLAMOS</a> has done with his LoRaWAN field tester.  Slaven started GLAMOS just before Helium introduced LoRaWAN to a few hundred thousand people over the course of about 9 months.</p>
<p>The LoRaWAN field testers he was producing HAD to be beginner friendly; most of the new Helium entrants had never heard of LoRaWAN.  They wanted to know what coverage was like in their area, and it need to be push-button easy.</p>
<p>The easier it is for someone to use a system, whether it’s a field test device like the GLAMOS or a soil moisture sensor, the better.  In fact, by making a device much easier to use you can increase the value of the thing, something that that Harmony Analytica does with their soil moisture sensor.</p>
<p>Sure, you can order a <a href="https://www.robotshop.com/products/makerfabs-lorawan-temperature-humidity-soil-moisture-sensor-915mhz?" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MakerFabs soil moisture sensor from Robot Shop</a> for $20 and even 3D print a <a href="https://www.printables.com/model/421370-makerfabs-soil-moisture-sensor-lorawan-housing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">cool little housing</a> for it, but then you have to program it, protect it from the elements (and lawnmowers), ruggedize it, then display its data or better yet, use the data to solve a problem.</p>
<p>All of those are value-add steps that Harmony Analytica offers in its $200 soil moisture sensor custom designed for the vertical of busy irrigation professionals.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="leverage-the-strengths">Leverage The Strengths<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/30/4-Ways-To-Improve-Your-LoRaWAN-Business#leverage-the-strengths" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Leverage The Strengths" title="Direct link to Leverage The Strengths">​</a></h3>
<p>We tend to forget about how good LoRaWAN is at solving certain problems, one of which is making almost anything, from sensor to skyscraper, smarter.</p>
<p>Manoj Telrandhe at <a href="https://www.terraq.tech/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TerraQ</a> does a great job highlighting this, and it has nothing to do with managing uplinks or what spreading factor was used; it's how much area one gateway can cover.</p>
<p>TerraQ deploys sensors throughout restaurants, adding HVAC monitoring, energy management (where he has a long history), and food compliance safety reporting.  As these restaurants expand, whether it’s knocking down a wall to make their space bigger or shifting down the street, adding a new sensor is as easy as putting in the batteries and sticking it on the wall (or the equipment.)</p>
<p>A LoRaWAN gateway can cover a huge area, so once you get that first gateway in, you’ve opened the door for up to 2,000 more sensors to deploy.  This is a massive advantage of LoRaWAN, and leaning into that wide area coverage should be on your business expansion checklist with any client.  You’ve got the coverage; why not use it?</p>
<p>The first and biggest cost is getting that gateway and first sensors installed; once it’s there, adding more sensors should be positioned as speeding up ROI. As Dean Marsh at <a href="https://www.ukconnect.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">UK Connect</a> says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’ve got to speak the language of ROI to the customer.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="be-unafraid-to-roam">Be Unafraid to Roam<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/30/4-Ways-To-Improve-Your-LoRaWAN-Business#be-unafraid-to-roam" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Be Unafraid to Roam" title="Direct link to Be Unafraid to Roam">​</a></h3>
<p>Since LoRaWAN is a wide area network, the chances are good that wherever you deploy, there’s already coverage there from another network.  Ignoring this can cost you and your clients money, which slows down ROI; never a good thing.</p>
<p>Test what’s available on site and don’t be afraid to figure out roaming agreements with other providers.  The most pervasive and easiest network to use (completely permissionless) will probably be Helium, a global community network with <a href="https://world.helium.com/en/iot/coverage" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">coverage across most of the developed world</a>.</p>
<p>Sign up for a free <a href="https://console.meteoscientific.com/front/login" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MeteoScientific Console account</a> and carry a field tester with you to your next potential client to test it out.  You get your first 400 Data Credits (24 byte each) for free, and I think you’ll be pleasantly surprised with the coverage.</p>
<p>This can make for a great demo to not have to set up a gateway.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Here’s your sensor, here’s your data.  Do you want this on a consistent basis?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From there you can provide your own gateways as needed to fill in the gaps, using <a href="https://www.disk91.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Paul Pinault’s</a> strategy of using a hybrid network approach to reduce downtime, increase reliability, and maximize ROI while maintaining control over data and encryption.</p>
<p>As Robert Bogs says of his deployment project <a href="https://kayna-funkt.de/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kayna-Funkt</a>, "With IoT you can have immediate impacts."  What more immediate impact than showing a business owner their data before you charge them anything?</p>
<p>However you use LoRaWAN, incorporating these 4 aspects will help you build your LoRaWAN business faster, better, and stronger.</p>
<ul>
<li>Start with a problem</li>
<li>Make it easy</li>
<li>Leverage the strengths</li>
<li>Be unafraid to roam</li>
</ul>
<p>Here's to you getting out there and gettin' after it, crushing sensor deployments, making the world a better, smarter place, and helping solve the number one problem in LoRaWAN.</p>
<p>Get 'em, friends!</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>Author</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p><strong>Nik Hawks</strong> is a LoRaWAN Educator &amp; Builder at <a href="https://meteoscientific.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MeteoScientific</a>. He writes to educate and delight people considering IoT, and to inspire other IoT nerds to build and deploy their own projects into the world. He runs a <a href="https://pod.metsci.show/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcast</a> discussing all things LoRaWAN and is psyched to hear about what you're building, whether it's a one sensor playground or a million sensor rollout.</p></div></div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="business" term="business"/>
        <category label="helium" term="helium"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Explore The Helium IoT Explorer]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer"/>
        <updated>2025-04-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the very first questions any reasonable business owner will have when they’re deciding whether or not to use LoRaWAN to connect their sensors to the internet is, “How do I get coverage?”]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the very first questions any reasonable business owner will have when they’re deciding whether or not to use LoRaWAN to connect their sensors to the internet is, “How do I get coverage?”</p>
<p>With LoRaWAN, you can deploy your own gateways and provide your own coverage, but as I've discussed on <a href="https://pod.metsci.show/episode/primer-lora-vs-lorawan-how-to-use-it" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this episode of the MetSci podcast</a> a few networks exist that already provide coverage and will give you free or very cheap access to it.  One of those is the <a href="https://world.helium.com/en/iot/hotspots" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Helium network</a>, a global LoRaWAN.</p>
<p>We’ll take a look at how to assess whether or not there is already Helium coverage in your area, and if it’s acceptable for your project. Let’s start at their coverage map, found at <a href="https://world.helium.com/en/mobile" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><code>world.helium.com</code></a>, which will default to Mobile.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Helium World Mobile Map" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/world-helium-mobile-c67981ac923473d7707b18c6b0367c91.png" width="1567" height="875" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Helium has 2 networks.  One is for IoT, and one is for phones.  We’re going to focus on the IoT network, which is the largest LoRaWAN network in the world with over 250,000 LoRaWAN gateways.</p>
<p>Helium calls these gateways “Hotspots” in an attempt to make this technology relatable to the average person.  I’ll use “gateway” and “hotspot” interchangeably here.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-hotspot-map">The Hotspot Map<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer#the-hotspot-map" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Hotspot Map" title="Direct link to The Hotspot Map">​</a></h3>
<p>We’ll start by exploring the Hotspot map, which you can find by <a href="https://world.helium.com/en/iot/hotspots" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">going to the green IoT button on the Helium IoT Explorer</a>, then clicking it to get dropdown options and selecting “Hotspot Map”.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Choose IoT Explorer" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/chose-green-iot-then-hotspot-map-a395e038bf291316abd51dbb05bf2766.png" width="1561" height="785" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>You should easily recognize the basic stats, like number of Hotspots and Daily Messages, but “DC burned” may be new to you.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Helium IoT Basic Stats" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/helium-basic-stats-bff0e84b60e78a8488d364f00af97ba5.png" width="1470" height="639" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Helium is a network powered by cryptocurrency.  The currency, or token, is called an HNT, or Helium Network Token.  It is used to <a href="https://docs.helium.com/tokens/data-credit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pay for data credits, or DCs, which allow you to transfer on the network</a>.</p>
<p>If you’d like, <strong>you can skip the whole cryptocurrency thing</strong> and just buy DCs with whatever currency you’re used to; dollars, euros, yen, whatever.  If you'd like to try that, you can do it over on the <a href="https://console.meteoscientific.com/front/login" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MeteoScientific Console</a>, although I give you the first 400 DC for free.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-cost-of-using-the-helium-network">The Cost Of Using The Helium Network<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer#the-cost-of-using-the-helium-network" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Cost Of Using The Helium Network" title="Direct link to The Cost Of Using The Helium Network">​</a></h3>
<p>One DC covers up to a 24 byte message and equals <code>$0.00001</code> USD.  Yes, that’s a thousandth of a penny.  Over on the MetSci Console (one of many LNS on Helium) I charge a 10x premium, which means you can still run a sensor sending <strong>a packet an hour for a year and spend less than a dollar.</strong></p>
<p>If you’re sending less than 24 bytes you still get charged for all 24.  If you’re sending more, you’ll get charged multiple DC per message.</p>
<p>You could also buy multiple copies of that message from multiple gateways.</p>
<p>Unlike traditional wireless networks, there is no subscription fee.  You just pay for the data you successfully transfer.</p>
<p>Helium is a permissionless network; there’s no sales staff to talk to first if you want to use it, no crazy sign up process, and if you’ve ever used LoRaWAN before, not much new to learn; you can just use it.  If you need help, check out my <a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/docs/tutorial-basics/LoRaWAN-Big-Picture" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tutorials</a>.</p>
<p>As you can see, Helium is staggeringly transparent.  On April 27th 2025 when I wrote this, 6.3 million messages had been transferred across the network in the last 24 hours at a cost of 10.4 million DC, or $104.81.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Transparent Data on Helium" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/staggeringly-transparent-costs-2b1f4591bd3868d762a4756dbc74f72d.png" width="1463" height="676" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>You can also see how many Hotspots (gateways) are currently serving the network, about 287,000 as of the time of writing.  If we just do some fast back-of-the-envelope math, you can see that what Helium did using token incentives to build a global LoRaWAN could not have been done in any traditional way.</p>
<p>If we price a gateway at $100 to buy and deploy, which is on the (very) cheap side, it would have cost a traditional network builder $28,740,000 to deploy today’s network.  Not every company has a cool $27 million to roll out a network.</p>
<p>That number, by the way, will probably shrink over time, stabilizing at (my GUESS) about 150,000 active gateways at any given time, probably providing the same coverage as you currently see with less redundancy.</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-note admonition_xJq3 alert alert--secondary"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>note</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>The reasons for the network's changing size go well beyond the scope of this article; if we meet for a coffee sometime I'll walk you through the whole arc of growth and all the deets.  For now, let's stick with exploring coverage.</p></div></div>
<p>The ongoing maintenance for gateways on the network is paid for by the people who deployed them, just like any network.  Many are run off their provided internet, but some (including some of mine) are on mountain tops and require a cell backhaul.</p>
<p>Those are ongoing costs borne by those who either want to earn cryptocurrency by adding something to their home network as well as those who, like me, use the network every day to pull in IoT data about my world, from weather stations to rain tank gauges to soil moisture.</p>
<p>Of course, you might zoom in on an area that doesn’t have a gateway and you want coverage there.  You can always deploy your own.  LoRaWAN gateways can be onboarded onto the Helium network, or you can buy a pre-onboarded one from a manufacturer like <a href="https://store.rakwireless.com/products/rak-hotspot-v2-with-free-rak2270-sticker-the-ultimate-tracking-bundle?variant=43023959523526" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RAK Wireless</a> and deploy it, in which case you’ll be able to use your coverage AND earn a little cryptocurrency.</p>
<p>That leads us to the Coverage map, which you’ll find by going to the green IoT tab at the top right, clicking on it to get the dropdown, and selecting “Coverage Map”.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Coverage Explorer on Helium" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/helium-coverage-map-cf2e9a94cef3e463015ca903dfe23b64.png" width="1560" height="797" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-does-a-gateway-cover">What Does a Gateway Cover?<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer#what-does-a-gateway-cover" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What Does a Gateway Cover?" title="Direct link to What Does a Gateway Cover?">​</a></h3>
<p>On the <code>IoT</code> --&gt; <code>Hotspot Map</code>, you can look for a specific Hotspot if you know its name. For example, <code>Quick Red Cobra</code> is one in downtown San Diego California, where I live.  Hotspots are assigned three-word names (Adjective-Color-Animal) randomly when they join the network.  This makes it easier for non-technical people to remember (and refer to) their hotspot.  Not everyone likes calling 'em a <code>UG56</code> or <code>SX1302 based</code> or the ol' <code>LPS8N</code>.</p>
<p>Let’s take a look at Quick Red Cobra and see what we can learn about the coverage this one gateway provides.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Quick Red Cobra Helium Hotspot" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/quick-red-cobra-c19b8ad6be151808361c75c4a9ddfc25.png" width="1562" height="882" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The first thing you'll probably notice is all the green hexes.  Helium uses the Uber h3 hex system to map out coverage, focusing on the resolution 8, or <code>res 8</code> sized hex, which is about .73 square kilometers.</p>
<p>Uber has written about this system extensively and open sourced it; you can <a href="https://www.uber.com/blog/h3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">learn more about it here</a>.</p>
<p>The very short version is that a hexagonal shape does a great job of consistently mapping a globe like our planet.  Using different size hexes allows you to map out an area of the world in any level of detail.</p>
<p>The sizes, or "resolutions", range from a <code>res 0</code> hex, of which there are only 110 in the world, each covering about 4.3 million square kilometers, all the way down to a <code>res 15</code> which has over 569 billion hexagons and maps to just under a square meter.</p>
<p>If you want to check out all the res sizes, <a href="https://h3geo.org/docs/core-library/restable" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here’s the list</a>.</p>
<p>If it’s good enough for Uber to find you at the airport among the other hundred people waiting in the rideshare lot, it's good enough to provide an excellent map of coverage for a LoRaWAN.</p>
<p>Every hotspot (or gateway, as you like) will cover a given number of <code>res 8</code> hexes.  Using the current coverage calculator, the Helium Explorer estimates that Quick Red Cobra has an expected coverage range of 500 hexes with at least a -130 dBm signal.  Not bad!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Quick Red Cobra Hexes covered" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/quick-red-cobra-hexes-covered-1464beff18d07468449a018f8ff46567.png" width="1540" height="655" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>How do you know a hex is covered?</p>
<p>You can use three methods; the easy way, the paid way, or the DIY way.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-easy-way-to-check-coverage">The Easy Way To Check Coverage<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer#the-easy-way-to-check-coverage" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Easy Way To Check Coverage" title="Direct link to The Easy Way To Check Coverage">​</a></h4>
<p>The easy way is to just look at what’s reported on this image.  In this case, the hotspot Quick Red Cobra has received data from 500 hexes.  This reported coverage data comes from a project called DIMO, which sells a vehicle data device called a Macaron that transmits information about a vehicle gathered from its OBD port via the Helium LoRaWAN.</p>
<p>If a vehicle with a DIMO Macaron has transmitted data from a hex covered by a gateway, that hex will show you the coverage strength and what gateways received the data.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-paid-way-to-check-coverage">The Paid Way to Check Coverage<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer#the-paid-way-to-check-coverage" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Paid Way to Check Coverage" title="Direct link to The Paid Way to Check Coverage">​</a></h4>
<p>The paid way is to use your own device, like a <a href="https://glamos.eu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GLAMOS mapper</a>.  You'd use your GLAMOS (or any mapper) to map a specific location, then assess the readings from your device using the GLAMOS app.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-diy-way-to-check-coverage">The DIY Way to Check Coverage<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer#the-diy-way-to-check-coverage" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The DIY Way to Check Coverage" title="Direct link to The DIY Way to Check Coverage">​</a></h4>
<p>The DIY way is to build your own mapping solution.  That's fun and rewarding, but for most instances, especially in the developed world where a ton of Hotspots are already deployed with plenty of DIMO vehicle traffic to map out signal, the Helium Coverage map is good enough, or for places where you're not sure (or need specific indoor coverage) the GLAMOS app fills in any gaps.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-about-coveragehere">What About Coverage...HERE?<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/04/27/Lets_Explore_Helium_Explorer#what-about-coveragehere" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What About Coverage...HERE?" title="Direct link to What About Coverage...HERE?">​</a></h3>
<p>Now, it’s likely that you’re more interested in actual coverage than which gateway is providing it.  For that, you can go <a href="https://world.helium.com/en/iot/coverage" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">back to the coverage map</a> and zoom in on any given area.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Grenoble Helium Coverage" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/grenoble-helium-coverage-c83cc4da68a077bc6843f16ca01dd693.png" width="1560" height="875" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>We’ll use the town of Grenoble in France for our example. I’ve zoomed in to it, and clicked on one of the green hexes in the Les Charmettes area.</p>
<p>Here we can see that 17 gateways provide coverage at better than -130 dBM for this hex, with a best RSSI of -83 dBm.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="17 Gateways In Grenoble" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/17-gateways-in-grenoble-b476540b5fb841eddf9c518359d457fe.png" width="1553" height="881" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>If you have specific dBm requirements, you can use the slider at the bottom right of the screen to set those.  For example, with a minimum RSSI of -108 dBm our redundancy drops to 9 gateways.  This is pretty much what I’d expect in the birthplace of LoRa; excellent coverage all around town.</p>
<p>Now, a global network does not equal ubiquitous coverage, and you’ll notice plenty of spots on the map where no coverage has been recorded.</p>
<p>If you need coverage in the mountains, or anywhere a vehicle can’t go, you can always grab any LoRaWAN device and fire off a few packets, or use the GLAMOS app, or buy a Helium Mapper from <a href="https://store.rakwireless.com/products/field-mapper-for-helium-with-plug-play-and-3rd-party-mode-rak10701-h?variant=43920609444038" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RAK</a> or <a href="https://www.seeedstudio.com/WioField-Tester-Kit-p-5282.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Seeed</a> to see what specific coverage is like.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Helium Field Mappers" src="https://www.meteoscientific.com/assets/images/helium-mappers-1174f9d1cfb6c903f30420895b33a2e8.png" width="800" height="300" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>You can also build your own Mapper <a href="https://docs.helium.com/iot/coverage-mapping/quickstart" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">following instructions</a> over on the Helium Docs site.</p>
<p>That wraps it for how to assess LoRaWAN coverage for anywhere in the world on the Helium network.  If you’d like to see coverage on other networks, excellent websites like <a href="https://www.coveragemap.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Coverage Map</a> offer maps of <a href="https://www.thethingsnetwork.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TTN</a> and other networks.</p>
<p>Not every LoRaWAN offers public mapping information like this (many of them have their own internal tools to manage and monitor their private networks), but if you’re looking for an easy way to see if there’s the kind of LoRaWAN coverage you need for your IoT solution, the Helium World Explorer is an excellent place to start.</p>
<p>Happy coverage hunting!</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>Author</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p><strong>Nik Hawks</strong> is a LoRaWAN Educator &amp; Builder at <a href="https://meteoscientific.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MeteoScientific</a>. He writes to educate and delight people considering IoT, and to inspire other IoT nerds to build and deploy their own projects into the world. He runs a <a href="https://pod.metsci.show/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcast</a> discussing all things LoRaWAN and is psyched to hear about what you're building, whether it's a one sensor playground or a million sensor rollout.</p></div></div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="business" term="business"/>
        <category label="helium" term="helium"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Actuarial IoT - When You Must Invest in IoT]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT"/>
        <updated>2025-02-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Implementing IoT (Internet of Things) solutions for monitoring and controlling utilities can yield substantial cost savings in water, electricity, sewer, gas, and HVAC usage.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Implementing IoT (Internet of Things) solutions for monitoring and controlling utilities can yield substantial cost savings in water, electricity, sewer, gas, and HVAC usage.</p>
<p>This analysis provides data-backed justification for IoT adoption across five major U.S. cities – <strong>New York</strong>, <strong>Los Angeles</strong>, <strong>Chicago</strong>, <strong>Houston</strong>, and <strong>San Francisco</strong> – focusing on utility rates, the business size thresholds where IoT becomes financially compelling, and ROI estimates for key sectors (retail, hotels, offices).</p>
<p>The goal is to equip CFOs and financial decision-makers with clear evidence that IoT-based efficiency is not just sustainable but economically <strong>essential</strong>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bottom-line-up-front">Bottom Line Up Front<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#bottom-line-up-front" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bottom Line Up Front" title="Direct link to Bottom Line Up Front">​</a></h2>
<p>Utility prices in most cases mean even moderate inefficiencies translate to real dollars. For example, <strong>1 CCF</strong> of wasted water in NYC (~748 gallons) costs a business ~$12 in water/sewer charges (<a href="https://www.nyc.gov/site/nycwaterboard/rates/rates-regulations.page#:~:text=2025%207%2F1%2F24,33" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rates &amp; Regulations - Water Board</a>); in LA, closer to $15.</p>
<p>Every <strong>1,000 kWh</strong> of unnecessary electrical usage in California costs ~$182; in New York ~$177; even in cheaper Illinois it’s ~$115. These recurring expenses establish a strong baseline for IoT savings potential.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="when-does-iot-make-financial-sense-thresholds-by-size">When Does IoT Make Financial Sense? (Thresholds by Size)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#when-does-iot-make-financial-sense-thresholds-by-size" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to When Does IoT Make Financial Sense? (Thresholds by Size)" title="Direct link to When Does IoT Make Financial Sense? (Thresholds by Size)">​</a></h2>
<p>IoT implementations require upfront investment (sensors, devices, software integration), so a common question is: <strong>at what point (in building size or headcount) do the savings justify the cost?</strong> Key factors include the building’s square footage, occupancy, and baseline utility consumption:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Building Size Threshold:</strong> Large facilities tend to waste more absolute energy/water, making IoT controls more immediately cost-effective. Traditionally, <strong>buildings larger than 50,000 sq ft</strong> were the domain of full Building Management Systems (BMS).</li>
</ul>
<p>In fact, over <a href="https://buildings.honeywell.com/content/dam/hbtbt/en/documents/downloads/Small%20and%20medium%20buildings_WHP-21-12-2022.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">90% of U.S. commercial buildings under 50k sq ft lack a proper BMS</a> to manage energy, even though the <strong>average commercial building wastes ~30%</strong> of the energy it consumes.</p>
<p>IoT now bridges this gap by offering “lighter” solutions suitable for <strong>smaller buildings</strong>. Modern IoT-based systems are <strong>wireless and modular</strong>, <a href="https://zenatix.com/how-is-iot-enabling-energy-savings-with-quick-roi/#:~:text=On%20the%20one%20hand%2C%20traditional,effectiveness%20and%20ease%20of%20deployment" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">avoiding the high CAPEX of traditional BMS</a>. This means <strong>even buildings less than 50k sq ft or with modest staff</strong> can achieve ROI, whereas before they couldn’t justify a full-scale automation system.</p>
<p><strong>Headcount and Usage:</strong> More employees typically mean more devices, lighting, HVAC load, and water use (restrooms, etc.). However, headcount correlates imperfectly with usage – <strong>square footage and operating hours are better metrics.</strong></p>
<p>For example, a <strong>10,000 sq ft retail store</strong> with 5 employees open 90 hours a week may use far more energy than a <strong>20,000 sq ft office</strong> with 50 employees that operates 40 hours a week. <strong>IoT becomes compelling when a business’s annual utility bills are high enough that a 10–20% savings offsets IoT project costs within a few years.</strong></p>
<p>In practice, many find this threshold at roughly <strong>$50,000+ in annual utility spend</strong>, which could correspond to a ~<strong>20,000+ sq ft office</strong> or a <strong>50,000 sq ft retail</strong> building (<a href="https://www.costanalysts.com/average-retail-electric-bill/#:~:text=Example%3A" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">depending on usage intensity</a>) . At that point, even a modest percentage savings translates to thousands of dollars.</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-note admonition_xJq3 alert alert--secondary"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>note</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>An average U.S. retail building uses ~14.3 kWh electricity and 30.9 cubic feet of gas per square foot yearly (<a href="https://www.costanalysts.com/average-retail-electric-bill/#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20Energy%20Information,the%20climate%20they%20operate%20in" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Average Electric Cost for Retail Store</a>).</p></div></div>
<p>That equates to about <strong>$1.76 per sq ft per year</strong> in energy costs (<a href="https://www.costanalysts.com/average-retail-electric-bill" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">using national average $1.47 for electricity + $0.29 for gas</a>). A <strong>50,000 sq ft retail store</strong> spends roughly <strong>$90,000/year on energy</strong>. If IoT solutions (smart thermostats, lighting controls, etc.) can save ~15%, that’s ~$13,500/year saved.</p>
<p>Even after equipment and installation, this size store sees a <strong>payback in under 2 years</strong>. Smaller stores (5,000–10,000 sq ft) with maybe $10k–$20k annual energy bills might see a longer payback (3–5 years), but often still within the useful life of the IoT equipment.</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-note admonition_xJq3 alert alert--secondary"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>note</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>Office buildings have slightly lower energy intensity than retail. A <strong>100,000 sq ft “large” office</strong> uses around <a href="https://remotefillsystems.com/how-much-power-does-an-office-building-use" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">20 kWh of electricity and 24 cubic feet of gas per sq ft annually</a>, costing on the order of ~$4 per sq ft (depending on local rates). That’s ~$400,000/year in utilities.</p></div></div>
<p>Even a <strong>20,000 sq ft</strong> office (perhaps ~100 employees) might spend $80k/year. As with retail, once you cross roughly <strong>five figures in annual utility costs</strong>, IoT controls become a “no-brainer” – many offices easily meet this with just HVAC and lighting. Notably, small offices (less than 5,000 sq ft) using ~13 kWh/sq ft (<a href="https://esource.bizenergyadvisor.com/article/small-and-midsize-offices#:~:text=Small%20and%20Midsize%20Offices%20,of%20electricity" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Small and Midsize Offices - Orlando Utilities Commission</a>) might have annual bills in the single-digit thousands; IoT can still help, but the <strong>financial “burn” is less acute</strong>.</p>
<p>In those cases, IoT is often justified more by <strong>comfort, sustainability goals, or preventive maintenance</strong> than immediate cost savings.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bottom-line">Bottom line:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#bottom-line" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bottom line:" title="Direct link to Bottom line:">​</a></h2>
<p>If your business occupies a mid-size or larger space – e.g. <strong>&gt;10,000 sq ft for retail</strong>, <strong>&gt;15,000 sq ft for offices</strong>, or <strong>any size hotel</strong> – you likely have enough utility expense that IoT improvements will <strong>pay for themselves quickly</strong>. Even smaller footprints with energy-intensive operations (restaurants, data closets, etc.) can benefit.</p>
<p>The days when only skyscrapers or factories could justify automation are over – IoT has <strong>lowered the entry barrier</strong> so that <strong>small and medium businesses</strong> can see ROI as well (<a href="https://zenatix.com/how-is-iot-enabling-energy-savings-with-quick-roi/#:~:text=2,buildings%2C%20ignoring%20the%20small%20infrastructures" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How is IoT enabling energy savings with quick ROI? - Zenatix by Schneider Electric</a>) (<a href="https://zenatix.com/how-is-iot-enabling-energy-savings-with-quick-roi/#:~:text=,energy%20savings" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How is IoT enabling energy savings with quick ROI? - Zenatix by Schneider Electric</a>).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="business-category-breakdown">Business Category Breakdown<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#business-category-breakdown" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Business Category Breakdown" title="Direct link to Business Category Breakdown">​</a></h2>
<p>Let’s examine how IoT-driven efficiency plays out in three key business categories – <strong>retail, hotels, and offices</strong> – which each have different usage patterns and opportunities. We’ll identify typical cost structures and how IoT can cut waste, with an eye on break-even points.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="retail-spaces-shops-malls-big-box-stores">Retail Spaces (Shops, Malls, Big-Box Stores)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#retail-spaces-shops-malls-big-box-stores" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Retail Spaces (Shops, Malls, Big-Box Stores)" title="Direct link to Retail Spaces (Shops, Malls, Big-Box Stores)">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Usage Profile:</strong> Retail properties consume about <strong>18 kWh of electricity per sq ft annually</strong> on average (<a href="https://www.lonestarpace.com/why-retail-property-owners-should-consider-energy-and-water-upgrades-090221bfprt/#:~:text=As%20retail%20property%20owners%20adjust,of%20usage" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Why Retail Property Owners Should Consider Energy and Water Upgrades - Lone Star PACE</a>) (or <strong>~14.3 kWh</strong> according to EIA (<a href="https://www.costanalysts.com/average-retail-electric-bill/#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20Energy%20Information,the%20climate%20they%20operate%20in" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Average Electric Cost for Retail Store [+ How to Cut Your Bill]</a>), varying by source) and significant heating fuel for large spaces.</p>
<p>A notable ~<strong>60% of that energy goes to lighting and HVAC</strong> (<a href="https://www.lonestarpace.com/why-retail-property-owners-should-consider-energy-and-water-upgrades-090221bfprt/#:~:text=As%20retail%20property%20owners%20adjust,of%20usage" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Why Retail Property Owners Should Consider Energy and Water Upgrades - Lone Star PACE</a>) – lighting alone often ~25% (<a href="https://www.lonestarpace.com/why-retail-property-owners-should-consider-energy-and-water-upgrades-090221bfprt/#:~:text=As%20retail%20property%20owners%20adjust,of%20usage" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Why Retail Property Owners Should Consider Energy and Water Upgrades - Lone Star PACE</a>). Water use in retail is relatively low (primarily restrooms and maybe landscaping), but can still add up in malls or stores with public facilities.</p>
<p><strong>Costs:</strong> As noted, U.S. retail spends about <strong>$1.47/sqft on electricity and $0.29/sqft on gas annually</strong> (<a href="https://www.costanalysts.com/average-retail-electric-bill/#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20Energy%20Information,the%20climate%20they%20operate%20in" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Average Electric Cost for Retail Store [+ How to Cut Your Bill]</a>) (climate dependent).</p>
<p>In high-rate cities like LA or SF, that electricity cost can double. <strong>Lighting, cooling, and heating comprise 70–84%</strong> of a typical retail building’s energy use (<a href="https://www.costanalysts.com/average-retail-electric-bill/#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20Energy%20Information,the%20climate%20they%20operate%20in" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Average Electric Cost for Retail Store [+ How to Cut Your Bill]</a>), meaning efficiency here yields big wins.</p>
<p><strong>IoT Opportunities:</strong> Smart lighting systems (LED retrofits with IoT controls, occupancy sensors, daylight harvesting) can dramatically cut lighting waste – e.g. dimming or shutting off lights in unoccupied store sections or after hours.</p>
<p>Smart thermostats and HVAC controls adjust temperatures based on occupancy or even foot traffic patterns. IoT sensors on refrigeration units can optimize defrost cycles and alert to energy-wasting faults (important for grocery retail).</p>
<p><strong>Savings &amp; ROI:</strong> Energy audits frequently find <strong>15–25% savings</strong> potential in retail via efficiency (<a href="https://www.lonestarpace.com/why-retail-property-owners-should-consider-energy-and-water-upgrades-090221bfprt/#:~:text=You%20have%20an%20opportunity%20to,month%2C%20impacting%20your%20bottom%20line" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Why Retail Property Owners Should Consider Energy and Water Upgrades - Lone Star PACE</a>). IoT control of lighting/HVAC can often realize <strong>15–20% reduction in energy use</strong> without compromising comfort or sales ambiance.</p>
<p>For a big retail store spending $90k/year on energy, a 20% cut saves ~$18k annually – directly boosting profit. <strong>Payback periods</strong> are often in the <strong>1–3 year range</strong> for IoT lighting and HVAC upgrades in retail. For example, simply optimizing lighting schedules and HVAC setpoints with IoT can shave thousands off the monthly bill for a big-box retailer.</p>
<p>Financing tools like C-PACE are even enabling <strong>immediate positive cash flow</strong> by spreading project costs, reinforcing that these upgrades “pay for themselves.” In short, for retail chains and large stores, IoT-based energy management is <strong>financially compelling</strong> – it turns one of the largest operating costs into an opportunity for savings.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hotels-and-lodging">Hotels and Lodging<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#hotels-and-lodging" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hotels and Lodging" title="Direct link to Hotels and Lodging">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Usage Profile:</strong> Hotels are utility-intensive, operating 24/7 with varying occupancy. U.S. hotels and motels consume roughly <strong>14 kWh of electricity and 49 cubic feet of natural gas per square foot each year</strong> (<a href="https://www.chegg.com/homework-help/questions-and-answers/hotels-motels-typically-use-average-14-kilowatt-hours-kwh-electricity-49-cubic-feet-natura-q87845412#:~:text=Chegg,square%20foot%20annually%2C%20according" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Solved Hotels and motels typically use an average of 14 | Chegg.com</a>) – <em>one of the highest energy intensities of any commercial building</em>. They also use large volumes of water for guest rooms (showers, toilets), laundry, pools, etc., all of which then require sewer treatment.</p>
<p><strong>Costs:</strong> Utilities can account for 4–6% of a hotel’s operating costs or more. Using the above usage figures, a <strong>100,000 sq ft hotel</strong> (around ~150 rooms, 4 floors) might use ~1.4 million kWh and 4.9 million cubic ft of gas annually.</p>
<p>At California rates (~18¢/kWh, ~$1/therm), that’s on the order of <strong>$300k+ per year</strong> in energy costs. Water/sewer bills in a large hotel can also be hefty (millions of gallons per year). This high baseline means <strong>even single-digit percentage improvements</strong> yield big dollar savings.</p>
<p><strong>IoT Opportunities:</strong> Hotels benefit greatly from <strong>smart HVAC and occupancy-based controls</strong>. Guestrooms are often unoccupied for large parts of the day – IoT occupancy sensors and smart thermostats can set back temperature setpoints when rooms are empty or guests are asleep, without compromising comfort.</p>
<p>Smart hotel thermostats and integrated energy management systems (EMS) have proven especially effective: they <strong>continuously analyze thermal behavior, weather, and peak loads to optimize HVAC in real-time</strong> (<a href="http://verdant.copeland.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Increasing-Profitability-with-IoT-Technology.pdf#:~:text=While%20smart%20thermostats%20and%20occupancy,6%2C%20and%20generate%20some%20of" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>) (<a href="http://verdant.copeland.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Increasing-Profitability-with-IoT-Technology.pdf#:~:text=IoT%20energy%20savings%2C%20moreover%2C%20are,Other%20HVAC%20devices%20Water%20consumption" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>). IoT leak sensors on pipes and fixtures can catch running toilets or drips that would otherwise go unnoticed (important for water conservation).</p>
<p>Common area lighting, pool pumps, and even kitchen equipment can be IoT-scheduled or monitored for efficiency. Hotels also leverage IoT for <strong>predictive maintenance</strong> – e.g. sensing when a chiller or boiler is losing efficiency and needs tune-up, avoiding energy waste and downtime.</p>
<p><strong>Savings &amp; ROI:</strong> The potential is dramatic. Smart energy management systems (like Verdant’s hotel IoT solution) <strong>can reduce hotel energy costs by up to 20%</strong> (<a href="http://verdant.copeland.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Increasing-Profitability-with-IoT-Technology.pdf#:~:text=EI,Verdant%20Energy%20Management%20Thermostats%20Lightning" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>). Hotels that have deployed IoT thermostats and occupancy sensors routinely see <strong>10–20% heating/cooling savings</strong> with <strong>payback periods of 12–24 months</strong> – among the fastest in the industry (<a href="http://verdant.copeland.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Increasing-Profitability-with-IoT-Technology.pdf#:~:text=EI,Verdant%20Energy%20Management%20Thermostats%20Lightning" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>). For instance, a case study showed a hotel cutting <strong>20% of its overall electric bill</strong>, translating to ~$14.5k saved in the first year for one limited-service property (<a href="http://verdant.copeland.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Increasing-Profitability-with-IoT-Technology.pdf#:~:text=savings%20after%20year%20one%20are,By%20the" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>).</p>
<p>Those savings continued each year, essentially paying back the IoT investment quickly and then compounding. Another analysis by Schneider Electric’s Zenatix notes that IoT-based building solutions often achieve <strong>ROI in 12–18 months</strong>, whereas older BMS took 3–5 years (<a href="https://zenatix.com/how-is-iot-enabling-energy-savings-with-quick-roi/#:~:text=periods%20%2812,5%20years" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How is IoT enabling energy savings with quick ROI? - Zenatix by Schneider Electric</a>). Beyond energy, water savings (from detecting leaks or optimizing laundry cycles) can add to the ROI – and in cities with Tiered water rates or fines for overuse, avoiding waste has direct payback.</p>
<p>In many cases, large hotels see annual savings in the six figures, meaning IoT investments can pay for themselves in <strong>well under 2 years</strong> and then continue saving money long-term.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="offices-corporate-and-commercial-office-buildings">Offices (Corporate and Commercial Office Buildings)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#offices-corporate-and-commercial-office-buildings" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Offices (Corporate and Commercial Office Buildings)" title="Direct link to Offices (Corporate and Commercial Office Buildings)">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Usage Profile:</strong> Office buildings primarily use electricity for lighting, computers, and HVAC, and use natural gas or steam for heating. Occupancy is typically 8–12 hours on weekdays, with off-hours presenting big savings opportunities.</p>
<p>Energy use intensity for offices averages <strong>15–22 kWh per sq ft/year</strong> (lower for small offices ~13 kWh, higher for large offices ~20 kWh) (<a href="https://esource.bizenergyadvisor.com/article/small-and-midsize-offices#:~:text=Small%20and%20Midsize%20Offices%20,of%20electricity" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Small and Midsize Offices - Orlando Utilities Commission</a>) (<a href="https://remotefillsystems.com/how-much-power-does-an-office-building-use/#:~:text=Systems%20remotefillsystems,annually%20by%20large%20office%20buildings" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How Much Power Does An Office Building Use? - Remote Fill Systems</a>), plus heating fuel. Water use in offices is mostly sanitary (bathrooms) and some cooling tower water for HVAC in larger buildings.</p>
<p><strong>Costs:</strong> For an <strong>office tower in NYC or SF</strong>, annual electricity bills can reach millions of dollars.</p>
<p>Even a <strong>50,000 sq ft office</strong> in Chicago might spend on the order of $100k/year across electricity and heating. Notably, <strong>about 30% of the energy in the average office is wasted</strong> due to inefficiencies (<a href="https://buildings.honeywell.com/content/dam/hbtbt/en/documents/downloads/Small%20and%20medium%20buildings_WHP-21-12-2022.pdf#:~:text=%E2%80%A2%20Reporting%20on%20small%20and,noted%20that%20the%20average%20commercial" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Small &amp; Medium Buildings Report | Honeywell</a>) – e.g. lights left on, HVAC running in empty spaces, etc.</p>
<p><strong>IoT Opportunities:</strong> Offices can leverage a <strong>suite of IoT solutions</strong>: Smart lighting systems that dim or shut off lights in unoccupied rooms or when daylight is sufficient; occupancy sensors and scheduling to power down HVAC in zones that are empty or after hours; smart plugs to cut power to idle equipment (copiers, coffee machines) overnight; and air quality sensors to optimize ventilation (bring in fresh air only as needed rather than running fans full-time).</p>
<p>Modern <strong>AI-driven building management</strong> can even adjust in real-time – for example, learning daily occupancy patterns and <strong>reducing HVAC output in lightly used areas to save energy</strong>, or pre-cooling a building just enough to avoid a demand charge peak (<a href="https://www.build-news.com/smart-infrastructure-and-urban-development/smart-building-technologies/ai-powered-building-systems-are-slashing-energy-costs-by-30/#:~:text=Advanced%20AI%20algorithms%20are%20revolutionizing,control%20over%20their%20building%E2%80%99s%20performance" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AI-Powered Building Systems Are Slashing Energy Costs by 30% - Industrial Build News</a>) (<a href="https://www.build-news.com/smart-infrastructure-and-urban-development/smart-building-technologies/ai-powered-building-systems-are-slashing-energy-costs-by-30/#:~:text=minimizing%20energy%20waste,improving%20efficiency%20strategies%20over%20time" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AI-Powered Building Systems Are Slashing Energy Costs by 30% - Industrial Build News</a>). Predictive maintenance via IoT (monitoring vibration/efficiency of fans, pumps, compressors) prevents equipment faults that can cause energy spikes.</p>
<p><strong>Savings &amp; ROI:</strong> Smart office implementations regularly achieve <strong>15–30% energy savings</strong> compared to traditional control (<a href="https://www.build-news.com/smart-infrastructure-and-urban-development/smart-building-technologies/ai-powered-building-systems-are-slashing-energy-costs-by-30/#:~:text=This%20dynamic%20approach%20typically%20results,equipment%20failures%20and%20extends%20the" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AI-Powered Building Systems Are Slashing Energy Costs by 30% - Industrial Build News</a>). A McKinsey study found that connected building technologies can trim <strong>office building energy use by 20–25% on average</strong> (and up to 50% in some cases) (<a href="https://www.autodesk.com/design-make/articles/smart-building#:~:text=Next," target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Next-gen smart buildings will run cheaper and greener - Autodesk</a>).</p>
<p>These reductions have huge ROI because offices often pay premium rates for peak usage – IoT systems that <strong>shave peak demand</strong> (e.g. by precooling before peak hours and dialing back at expensive times) directly reduce utility bills.</p>
<p>Many offices see a <strong>payback in ~2 years or less</strong> for lighting + HVAC IoT retrofits. For example, an AI-based HVAC optimization in an office portfolio can yield ~30% savings with ROI under 3 years (<a href="https://ewattch.com/en/solutions/solution-energetique-batiments-tertiaires/#:~:text=Smart%20Building%20,Start%20your" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Smart Building - IOT solutions - Ewattch</a>), and some IoT providers advertise ROI less than <strong>3 months</strong> for certain optimizations in commercial buildings (<a href="https://ewattch.com/en/solutions/solution-energetique-batiments-tertiaires/#:~:text=Smart%20Building%20,Start%20your" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Smart Building - IOT solutions - Ewattch</a>) (likely in very wasteful pre-IoT scenarios).</p>
<p>Even <strong>small offices</strong> benefit: cloud-based IoT building platforms are allowing small/medium offices to get <strong>BMS-like savings (20–30% cuts) at a fraction of the cost</strong> (<a href="https://zenatix.com/how-is-iot-enabling-energy-savings-with-quick-roi/#:~:text=2,buildings%2C%20ignoring%20the%20small%20infrastructures" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How is IoT enabling energy savings with quick ROI? - Zenatix by Schneider Electric</a>) (<a href="https://zenatix.com/how-is-iot-enabling-energy-savings-with-quick-roi/#:~:text=,energy%20savings" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How is IoT enabling energy savings with quick ROI? - Zenatix by Schneider Electric</a>).</p>
<p>One whitepaper noted a small office pilot that <strong>achieved 29% energy savings in under 3 months</strong> using an IoT retrofit (<a href="https://buildings.honeywell.com/content/dam/hbtbt/en/documents/downloads/Small%20and%20medium%20buildings_WHP-21-12-2022.pdf#:~:text=Achieved%2029,an%20average%20of%204%2C273%20kilowatt" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Small &amp; Medium Buildings Report | Honeywell</a>). The <strong>bottom line for offices</strong> is that IoT not only pays for itself but often contributes to significant operational cost reduction, improved occupant comfort (which can indirectly boost productivity), and even higher property value – efficient buildings command higher rents and asset values (<a href="https://www.wegowise.com/resources/financial-impact-of-energy-and-water-savings#:~:text=,property%20to%20an%20entire%20portfolio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impact of Energy and Water Savings on Multifamily Properties | WegoWise</a>) (<a href="https://www.wegowise.com/resources/financial-impact-of-energy-and-water-savings#:~:text=Energy%20and%20water%20benchmarking%20and,a%20fast%20time%20to%20value" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impact of Energy and Water Savings on Multifamily Properties | WegoWise</a>).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="other-industries-with-strong-iot-justification">Other Industries with Strong IoT Justification<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#other-industries-with-strong-iot-justification" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Other Industries with Strong IoT Justification" title="Direct link to Other Industries with Strong IoT Justification">​</a></h2>
<p>While retail, hospitality, and offices are prime candidates, <strong>many other industries</strong> also see exceptional ROI from IoT-driven efficiency:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Manufacturing &amp; Industrial:</strong> Factories and industrial plants often have <em>massive</em> energy consumption (electric motors, process heat, compressed air systems) and water usage (for cooling or processes).</li>
</ul>
<p>IoT sensors enable <strong>predictive maintenance</strong> (avoiding inefficient operation and downtime) and continuous energy monitoring. According to Deloitte, IoT-based predictive maintenance can cut maintenance costs <strong>up to 25%</strong> and reduce unplanned downtime by <strong>up to 50%</strong> (<a href="https://hexastate.com/investing-in-the-future-how-predictive-maintenance-can-drive-roi/#:~:text=ROI%20hexastate,downtime%20by%20up%20to%2050" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Investing in the Future: How Predictive Maintenance Can Drive ROI</a>) – improvements that directly protect revenue and reduce waste.</p>
<p>The ROI here comes not only from utility savings but from <strong>increased production uptime</strong>. Many manufacturers see IoT projects pay off within 1–2 years just from maintenance savings and energy efficiency (e.g. shutting off idle equipment, optimizing HVAC in warehouses, etc.).</p>
<p>Industrial facilities also often face demand charges; IoT controls can stagger equipment startups and <strong>reduce peak load</strong>, saving on those charges.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Data Centers &amp; Tech Facilities:</strong> Data centers are energy hogs (powering servers and cooling them). IoT sensors and AI can optimize <strong>cooling systems (HVAC)</strong> – for example, adjusting setpoints and airflow to match server load or using outside air cooling when conditions allow.</li>
</ul>
<p>Even a 1% improvement in PUE (power usage effectiveness) can translate to tens of thousands of dollars in large data centers. IoT monitoring can also prevent thermal runaway or pinpoint hot spots to avoid overcooling.</p>
<p>Many data centers have implemented IoT-driven dynamic cooling and seen <strong>payback in well under 2 years</strong> due to the enormous energy baseline.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Healthcare (Hospitals):</strong> Hospitals operate 24/7 with intensive HVAC and water demands (sterilization, laundry, etc.). They often have older infrastructure that runs continuously.</li>
</ul>
<p>IoT building management in hospitals can safely reduce HVAC usage in unoccupied zones (or at night in administrative areas), monitor medical refrigeration units, and detect water leaks (important for infection control and cost).</p>
<p>Given that hospitals in high-cost regions can spend $5–$10 million a year on utilities, even a 10% savings is huge. Many hospitals are finding IoT upgrades (sometimes funded through energy performance contracts) that deliver ROI in ~3 years and then free up funds to reinvest in patient care.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multifamily Residential:</strong> Apartment complexes and commercial residential buildings benefit from IoT through smart thermostats, leak detectors, and boiler controls. While not “industrial,” this sector sees strong financial cases for IoT because utility costs often either eat into NOI or are passed to tenants who demand efficiency.</li>
</ul>
<p>Analytics on energy and water use in multifamily buildings can <strong>increase NOI and property value significantly</strong>, with benchmarking software creating <strong>payback in mere months</strong> for owners (<a href="https://www.wegowise.com/resources/financial-impact-of-energy-and-water-savings#:~:text=,property%20to%20an%20entire%20portfolio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impact of Energy and Water Savings on Multifamily Properties | WegoWise</a>). For example, finding and fixing water leaks or insulating a building after IoT data analysis can yield immediate savings that increase an apartment building’s net income (and thus its appraised value) by hundreds of thousands (<a href="https://www.wegowise.com/resources/financial-impact-of-energy-and-water-savings#:~:text=,property%20to%20an%20entire%20portfolio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impact of Energy and Water Savings on Multifamily Properties | WegoWise</a>) (<a href="https://www.wegowise.com/resources/financial-impact-of-energy-and-water-savings#:~:text=,property%20to%20an%20entire%20portfolio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impact of Energy and Water Savings on Multifamily Properties | WegoWise</a>).</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Agriculture and Irrigation:</strong> In farming, IoT soil moisture sensors and smart irrigation systems drastically reduce water usage (sometimes by 30–50%) while improving crop yield. Water is a major cost in agriculture; IoT systems often pay for themselves in <strong>one growing season</strong> by eliminating overwatering and runoff.</li>
</ul>
<p>This may be outside typical “business office” environments, but for agribusiness CFOs the financial logic is analogous: <strong>spend on IoT to save on water</strong> (and energy for pumping) – it’s a quick ROI and hedges against drought risks.</p>
<p>In each of these sectors, IoT projects are often <strong>self-funding through savings</strong>. A telling statistic: <strong>92% of enterprises report positive ROI</strong> from IoT implementations, according to a wide-ranging survey (<a href="https://www.75f.io/#:~:text=More" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">75F: The World's Most Advanced IoT Building Automation</a>).</p>
<p>The industries above are standouts because their pre-IoT utility costs (or maintenance costs) are so high that even modest efficiency gains translate into big financial wins.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="roi-estimates-and-payback-periods">ROI Estimates and Payback Periods<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#roi-estimates-and-payback-periods" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ROI Estimates and Payback Periods" title="Direct link to ROI Estimates and Payback Periods">​</a></h2>
<p>A data-backed financial analysis is critical for CFO approval. Fortunately, IoT efficiency investments generally have <strong>attractive ROI profiles</strong>. Here are some key points on returns and payback periods, along with examples:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Typical Payback:</strong> Most IoT energy management projects for buildings see payback within <strong>1 to 3 years</strong>. Lighting retrofits with IoT controls often pay back in ~1–2 years (thanks to power savings and utility rebates).</li>
</ul>
<p>HVAC IoT upgrades are often 2–3 years unless major equipment replacement is involved. These periods are <strong>well within the lifespan</strong> of the equipment, meaning strong net present value.</p>
<p>In fact, IoT-based solutions often <strong>outperform</strong> traditional capital projects on ROI – for example, IoT controls (12–18 month payback) vs. a chiller replacement (maybe a 7+ year payback).</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fast Payback Cases (Months, Not Years):</strong> There are numerous instances where IoT projects have <strong>paid for themselves in a matter of months</strong>. For example, an IoT retrofit in a large commercial building that optimized cooling and lighting achieved <strong>15% energy savings (~400,000 kWh/year)</strong> and paid back in <strong>just 5 months</strong> (<a href="https://www.iotforall.com/energy-efficient-cities-building-solutions-microgrids-iot#:~:text=IoT%20www,that%20building%20cooling%20and" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Energy Efficient Cities: Building-Level Solutions, Microgrids and IoT</a>).</li>
</ul>
<p>Another case: a building analytics software identified operational tweaks that created <strong>an immediate reduction in utility bills, achieving payback in under 6 months</strong> (<a href="https://www.wegowise.com/resources/financial-impact-of-energy-and-water-savings#:~:text=,property%20to%20an%20entire%20portfolio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impact of Energy and Water Savings on Multifamily Properties | WegoWise</a>). These “low-hanging fruit” scenarios are not universal, but they highlight that <em>some IoT improvements start contributing to the bottom line almost immediately</em>.</p>
<p>Usually, fast-payback items include things like scheduling controls (which cost little to implement but save a lot by turning things off) and fixing blatant issues (like a mis-programmed HVAC system running 24/7).</p>
<p>It's not uncommon for IoT investments to become net-positive within the same fiscal year of implementation for the most wasteful facilities.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi-Year ROI and TCO:</strong> When evaluating multi-year impact, IoT shines even more. A project with a 2-year payback yields a 50% annual ROI; over a 10-year period, that’s a huge cumulative return.</li>
</ul>
<p>IoT systems also often extend equipment life (through reduced run-time and predictive maintenance), which avoids capital expenditures – those avoided costs effectively improve the ROI when viewed holistically. For instance, if smart monitoring prevents a $50k catastrophic failure of a boiler that would have happened in year 3, that “saving” should be included.</p>
<p>Many CFOs therefore consider not just direct utility savings but also <strong>risk mitigation ROI</strong> (avoided damage, downtime, compliance fines, etc.) which IoT provides by giving early warning of issues.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>ROI in Financial Terms:</strong> CFOs may translate savings into familiar metrics like <strong>increase in EBITDA or asset value</strong>. Energy savings drop straight to the bottom line.</li>
</ul>
<p>For a property owner, reducing operating costs by $1 can increase asset value by $10–$20 (using cap rates of 5–10%). We saw an example where <strong>$69,700 in annual energy/water savings raised a multifamily property’s value by $610k–$1.16M</strong> (<a href="https://www.wegowise.com/resources/financial-impact-of-energy-and-water-savings#:~:text=,property%20to%20an%20entire%20portfolio" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Impact of Energy and Water Savings on Multifamily Properties | WegoWise</a>).</p>
<p>Similar logic applies to commercial buildings – an office building that saves $100k/yr in utilities could be worth $1–2 million more. Thus, IoT isn’t just cutting this year’s expenses, it’s <strong>building long-term enterprise value</strong>.</p>
<p>The ROI can be communicated in those terms for clarity – e.g., “This IoT upgrade has a 50% IRR and increases our building’s appraised value by $X million.”</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Real-world Benchmarks:</strong>
<ul>
<li><em>Hotels:</em> 15–20% energy savings, <strong>ROI ~50–100%</strong> (payback 1–2 years) (<a href="http://verdant.copeland.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Increasing-Profitability-with-IoT-Technology.pdf#:~:text=EI,Verdant%20Energy%20Management%20Thermostats%20Lightning" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>).</li>
<li><em>Offices:</em> 10–30% savings, ROI often <strong>30–80%</strong> (payback ~1.5–3 years). Many see positive cash flow from year 1 due to financing or phased roll-outs.</li>
<li><em>Retail:</em> 10–20% savings, ROI ~20–60% (payback ~2–4 years, faster for larger stores). The variance depends on store size and hours – 24-hour big boxes save more absolute energy and thus have faster ROI.</li>
<li><em>Industrial:</em> ROI can be extremely high when preventing costly downtime – often justified on reliability alone, with energy savings as a bonus (difficult to generalize a number, but many have seen multi-hundred-percent ROI just from avoiding one big failure).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>From the above analysis, it’s clear that <strong>IoT-driven efficiency is a financially savvy move</strong> for businesses in New York, Los Angeles, Chicago, Houston, San Francisco, and beyond. High utility rates in many of these cities magnify the value of saving each kilowatt-hour or gallon.</p>
<p>IoT implementations can often be justified purely on an actuarial cost-savings basis: by reducing waste (often ~15–30%), they slash recurring expenses and pay back rapidly.</p>
<p>Crucially, we identified that even mid-sized facilities (tens of thousands of square feet, or utility bills in the mid five-figures) reach the threshold where IoT is compelling.</p>
<p>No longer is IoT only for marquee skyscrapers or giant factories – <strong>it’s now an essential tool for cost control and sustainability in everyday businesses.</strong> Retail stores can curtail one of their largest operating costs, hotels can protect their thin margins from energy volatility, and offices can turn facility management into a source of savings.</p>
<p>Other industries like manufacturing, data centers, and healthcare are similarly ripe for IoT optimizations that bolster the bottom line.</p>
<p>For CFOs and financial decision-makers, the message is: <strong>investing in IoT solutions is not an experimental tech spree, but a prudent financial strategy</strong>. The data shows that these investments yield tangible returns – often boosting annual profits after a short payback period and continuing to generate savings year after year.</p>
<p>In many cases, IoT upgrades can be structured so that savings exceed costs from day one (via smart financing or phased implementation), making the decision even easier.</p>
<p>In sum, implementing IoT for utility management is a <strong>cost-saving measure with proven ROI</strong>, vital for business sustainability and competitiveness. Companies that embrace it will not only reduce expenses and improve their efficiency metrics; they’ll also enhance asset values and resilience against future utility cost increases.</p>
<p>As illustrated with the rates and examples for NYC, LA, Chicago, Houston, and SF, the numbers speak clearly: <strong>IoT is a smart investment that pays for itself – often quicker than expected – and continues paying dividends in operational savings.</strong></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="utility-cost-landscape-in-major-cities">Utility Cost Landscape in Major Cities<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#utility-cost-landscape-in-major-cities" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Utility Cost Landscape in Major Cities" title="Direct link to Utility Cost Landscape in Major Cities">​</a></h2>
<p>Utility rates vary widely by city and region. To compare costs, we’ve converted water and sewer rates to a common unit (CCF, or hundred cubic feet; <em>1 CCF ≈ 748 gallons</em>). Electricity is given in cents per kilowatt-hour (¢/kWh) and natural gas in dollars per therm (1 therm ≈ 100 cubic feet of gas). Below are <strong>official utility rates</strong> in each city:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-york-city-nyc">New York City (NYC)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#new-york-city-nyc" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New York City (NYC)" title="Direct link to New York City (NYC)">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Water:</strong> $4.49 per CCF; <strong>Sewer:</strong> $7.14 per CCF (159% of water rate) Combined, <a href="https://www.nyc.gov/site/nycwaterboard/rates/rates-regulations.page#:~:text=2025%207%2F1%2F24,33" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NYC businesses pay about <strong>$11.63 per CCF</strong></a> of water consumed.</p>
<p><strong>Electricity:</strong> ~17.7¢/kWh on average for commercial customers (<a href="https://www.eia.gov/electricity/monthly/epm_table_grapher.php?t=epmt_5_6_a#:~:text=New%20York%2024,51" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Electric Power Monthly - U.S. Energy Information Administration (EIA)</a>).</p>
<p><strong>Natural Gas:</strong> Approximately $1.00–$1.20 per therm (varies seasonally). New York’s water/sewer costs are relatively high (FY2025 rates rise to $4.87 + $7.74 = <strong>$12.61/CCF</strong> (<a href="https://www.nyc.gov/site/nycwaterboard/rates/rates-regulations.page#:~:text=2025%207%2F1%2F24,33" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rates &amp; Regulations - Water Board</a>)), making water efficiency critical.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="los-angeles-la">Los Angeles (LA)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#los-angeles-la" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Los Angeles (LA)" title="Direct link to Los Angeles (LA)">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Water:</strong> ~$9.39 per CCF (<a href="https://www.ladwp.com/account/customer-service/water-rates/schedule-c-commercial-industrial-governmental" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">City of LA, commercial Tier-1 rate mid-2024</a>). LADWP uses tiered pricing; heavy users pay up to ~$13.4/CCF in higher tiers.</p>
<p><strong>Sewer:</strong> $5.80 per CCF (<a href="https://sanitation.lacity.gov/cs/groups/sg_rates/documents/document/y250/mduw/~edisp/cnt050142.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">city wastewater charge</a>). Together, LA businesses effectively face ~$15 per CCF for water/sewer.</p>
<p><strong>Electricity:</strong> ~18.2¢/kWh for commercial accounts (<a href="https://www.eia.gov/electricity/monthly/epm_table_grapher.php?t=epmt_5_6_a#:~:text=match%20at%20L384%20California%2032,68" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">California average</a>).</p>
<p><strong>Natural Gas:</strong> ~$1.00–$1.10 per therm (SoCal Gas rates, varying with market prices).</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="chicago">Chicago<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#chicago" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Chicago" title="Direct link to Chicago">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Water:</strong> $35.10 per 1,000 cubic feet, i.e. <strong>$3.51 per CCF</strong> (<a href="https://www.chicago.gov/city/en/depts/fin/supp_info/utility-billing/water-and-sewer-rates.html#:~:text=Water%20Rate%20per%201%2C000%20Cubic,Feet" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">
City of Chicago :: Water and Sewer Rates
</a>);</p>
<p><strong>Sewer:</strong> charged at 100% of water usage (<a href="https://www.chicago.gov/city/en/depts/fin/supp_info/utility-billing/water-and-sewer-rates.html#:~:text=For%20both%20metered%20and%20non,front%20of%20the%20utility%20bills" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dollar-for-dollar</a>). This equals <strong>$3.51 per CCF</strong> for sewer, or about <strong>$7.02 per CCF combined</strong>.  Chicago’s water costs per volume are lower than coastal cities.</p>
<p><strong>Electricity:</strong> ~11.5¢/kWh <a href="https://www.eia.gov/electricity/monthly/epm_table_grapher.php?t=epmt_5_6_a#:~:text=New%20York%2024,51" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">on average for commercial users in Illinois</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Natural Gas:</strong> ~$0.95–$1.00 per therm (<a href="https://www.peoplesgas.com/4a5cbb/contentassets/76b6b8638ec743a18f041648c4c29bd1/july-2024-commercial-rates.pdf#:~:text=,%E2%80%A2%20Swing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Peoples Gas in Chicago has a 2024 cap at ~$0.97/therm</a>).</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="houston">Houston<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#houston" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Houston" title="Direct link to Houston">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Water:</strong> tiered by usage; in 2022 commercial rates were ~$5.55 per 1,000 gallons, rising to over $7.00 per 1,000 gallons by 2024 (<a href="https://www.houstontx.gov/citysec/HPW/ratestable.pdf#:~:text=Industrial%20All%20Usage%205,39" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>) (roughly <strong>$5.3 per CCF</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Sewer:</strong> similarly rising into the <del>$9+ per 1,000 gal range by 2024 (<a href="https://www.houstontx.gov/citysec/HPW/ratestable.pdf#:~:text=match%20at%20L294%20Commercial%20All,60" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"></a>) (</del><strong>$6.9 per CCF</strong>). Combined, Houston’s water/sewer runs around <strong>$12–$13 per CCF</strong> for high-volume users.</p>
<p><strong>Electricity:</strong> ~8.7¢/kWh average for Texas commercial customers (<a href="https://www.eia.gov/electricity/monthly/epm_table_grapher.php?t=epmt_5_6_a#:~:text=Texas%2015,71" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">energy costs are low due to deregulated markets</a>).</p>
<p><strong>Natural Gas:</strong> ~$0.50–$0.60 per therm (Texas enjoys low gas prices). <em>Houston’s relatively cheap electricity makes HVAC efficiency more about peak demand management than unit cost, while water is a growing expense.</em></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="san-francisco-sf">San Francisco (SF)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/13/Actuarial_IoT#san-francisco-sf" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to San Francisco (SF)" title="Direct link to San Francisco (SF)">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Water:</strong> SFPUC charges uniform rates for businesses; <a href="https://www.cityofpaloalto.org/files/assets/public/v/1/utilities/rates-schedules-for-utilities/prop-218-notice-fy25-final.pdf#:~:text=It%20is%20anticipated%20that%20beginning,to" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">wholesale cost to the city is ~$5.21/CCF</a>, with retail rates higher after distribution costs (on the order of ~$7–$8+ per CCF for end-users).</p>
<p><strong>Sewer:</strong> San Francisco’s combined sewer/stormwater system leads to high wastewater fees that depend on discharge volume and strength. For typical commercial waste strength, sewer rates per CCF can <strong>exceed water rates</strong> (often making total water + sewer &gt; <strong>$15 per CCF</strong>).</p>
<p><strong>Electricity:</strong> ~18¢/kWh for commercial users (<a href="https://www.eia.gov/electricity/monthly/epm_table_grapher.php?t=epmt_5_6_a#:~:text=match%20at%20L384%20California%2032,68" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">California average</a>) note SF’s electricity is delivered by PG&amp;E or CleanPowerSF at similar averages.</p>
<p><strong>Natural Gas:</strong> ~$1.10–$1.20 per therm (PG&amp;E gas rates). <em>San Francisco has some of the highest combined water-sewer costs, so water efficiency and leak detection IoT can yield particularly large savings.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="business" term="business"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[LoRaWAN In Elder Care]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/06/LoRaWAN_for_senior_tracking</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/06/LoRaWAN_for_senior_tracking"/>
        <updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Can you use LoRaWAN for emergencies?  Yep.  Semtech and iWOW Technology Ltd announced they've been running a LoRaWAN based emergency alert system in Singapore covering 10,000 public housing flats; that's a lot!]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Can you use LoRaWAN for emergencies?  Yep.  Semtech and iWOW Technology Ltd <a href="https://iotbusinessnews.com/2025/01/06/20510-semtech-and-iwow-enhance-elder-care-with-lorawan-wireless-emergency-system/?utm_source=chatgpt.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">announced they've been running a LoRaWAN based emergency alert system</a> in Singapore covering 10,000 public housing flats; that's a lot!</p>
<p>The system has been in place and running since 2019, and 6 years on 98% of the devices are still operational.  This is a classic example of elder care IoT solutions, bringing high tech to help with emergency alerts.</p>
<p>The system is simple; it's just a wall-mounted red button that anyone can press to route an emergency call to a 24 hour response center. Simultaneously, the app used notifies next of kin.</p>
<p>These types of systems also offer opportunities to the businesses providing them, as once you're providing coverage for emergency buttons you're also providing coverage for the rest of the building.</p>
<p>If you're building a LoRaWAN-based business, thinking about your gateway use case (pun intended) as just the beginning is a great way to enter a market.</p>
<p>Get 'em!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="senior care" term="senior care"/>
        <category label="emergency" term="emergency"/>
        <category label="alert" term="alert"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Global LoRaWAN Industry Analysis]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis"/>
        <updated>2025-02-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[History and Evolution of LoRaWAN]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="history-and-evolution-of-lorawan">History and Evolution of LoRaWAN<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#history-and-evolution-of-lorawan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to History and Evolution of LoRaWAN" title="Direct link to History and Evolution of LoRaWAN">​</a></h2>
<p>LoRaWAN's technological roots <a href="https://blog.semtech.com/a-brief-history-of-lora-three-inventors-share-their-personal-story-at-the-things-conference#:~:text=The%20story%20of%20LoRa%20began,technology%2C%20a%20technology%20widely%20in" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">date back to 2009 in Grenoble, France</a>, when Nicolas Sornin and Olivier Seller began experimenting with chirp spread spectrum (CSS) modulation for low-power, long-range communications​.</p>
<p>This led to the founding of Cycleo in 2010 with the goal of enabling wireless data links for utility meters using sub-GHz radio. Instead of inventing a new modulation from scratch, Cycleo applied CSS (a technique long used in sonar and radar) to IoT communications – essentially repurposing chirp signals for data transmission​. The breakthrough proved that kilometer-range wireless links could be achieved with very low power, ideal for battery-operated IoT sensors.</p>
<p>Seeing the potential, Semtech acquired Cycleo in 2012, gaining the LoRa IP and the small team of inventors​. Over the next few years, Semtech refined the technology into silicon – releasing chipsets like the <a href="https://www.semtech.com/products/wireless-rf/lora-connect/sx1272" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SX1272</a>/1276 transceivers for end devices and the multi-channel <a href="https://www.semtech.com/products/wireless-rf/lora-core/sx1301" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SX1301</a> for gateways​. With hardware in place, attention turned to creating a standardized networking protocol on top of LoRa.</p>
<p>In 2015, industry leaders including Semtech, Actility, and IBM formed the LoRa Alliance, which published the first LoRaWAN specification. LoRaWAN (Long Range Wide Area Network) defines the MAC-layer protocol and architecture for LoRa networks, enabling interoperability across vendors. The first LoRaWAN spec (v1.0) emerged around 2015, and the Alliance began promoting it as an open standard for Low Power WAN.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="early-adoption-20152017">Early Adoption (2015–2017)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#early-adoption-20152017" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Early Adoption (2015–2017)" title="Direct link to Early Adoption (2015–2017)">​</a></h3>
<p>LoRaWAN quickly gained traction, especially in Europe. By 2016, multiple telecom operators had launched LoRaWAN networks as a complement or alternative to cellular IoT. For example, Orange and Bouygues Telecom in France each deployed nationwide LoRaWAN coverage by 2016, <a href="https://www.rudebaguette.com/en/2015/09/taking-aim-at-sigfox-orange-announces-rollout-for-a-lora-based-iot-network-in-2016/#:~:text=Taking%20aim%20at%20SIGFOX%2C%20Orange,the%20first%20quarter%20of%202016" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">seeing LoRa as a ready solution for IoT</a> before NB-IoT was widely available​.</p>
<p>KPN in the Netherlands likewise <a href="https://www.sdxcentral.com/articles/news/sk-telecom-kpn-deploy-nationwide-lorawan-iot-networks/2016/07/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">rolled out a nationwide LoRaWAN network by mid-2016</a>, one of the first in the world​. In South Korea, <a href="https://www.samsung.com/global/business/networks/insights/press-release/samsung-electronics-to-jointly-build-skt-world-first-nationwide-lorawan-network-dedicated-to-iot/#:~:text=Samsung%20Electronics%20to%20jointly%20build,2016" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SK Telecom partnered with Samsung</a> to deploy a country-wide LoRaWAN network in 2016, offering IoT coverage spanning 99% of the population.</p>
<p>These early networks targeted applications like smart city sensors and asset tracking. Simultaneously, the open community model took off: <a href="https://www.thethingsnetwork.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Things Network</a>, launched in 2015 in Amsterdam, rallied volunteers to set up LoRaWAN gateways and provide free community coverage in hundreds of cities globally, demonstrating grassroots adoption.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="growth-and-maturity-20182021">Growth and Maturity (2018–2021)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#growth-and-maturity-20182021" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Growth and Maturity (2018–2021)" title="Direct link to Growth and Maturity (2018–2021)">​</a></h3>
<p>By 2018, LoRaWAN had achieved significant global footprint. The LoRa Alliance reported over <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/lora-alliance-press-release/lora-alliance-registra-una-crescita-del-66-delle-reti-pubbliche-lorawan-negli-ultimi-3-anni/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">100 network operators in 100+ countries by 2018</a>​. This included not just telecom-led public networks, but also private enterprise networks and community deployments.</p>
<p>Over these years, the LoRaWAN specification evolved (versions 1.1, 1.0.3 etc.) to add features like better security, roaming between networks, and firmware updates over-the-air. The ecosystem expanded with more device makers and solution providers joining the Alliance. Cumulative device deployments climbed into the tens of millions, driven by use cases in smart utilities, agriculture, and logistics. By 2020, Semtech estimated over 100 million devices were running on LoRa/LoRaWAN globally.</p>
<p>A major milestone in 2021 was <strong>LoRaWAN’s recognition by the ITU-T as an official international standard for LPWAN</strong>, <a href="https://www.melita.io/articles-news/lora-alliance-publishes-annual-report-global-expansion-of-the-lorawan-market-in-2022/#:~:text=The%20report%20reveals%20that%20LoRaWAN,and%20most%20diverse%20IoT%20ecosystem" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">cementing its status alongside cellular standards</a>​. This ITU approval (achieved in late 2021) underscored LoRaWAN’s maturity and interoperability as an open protocol.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="recent-developments-20222025">Recent Developments (2022–2025)<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#recent-developments-20222025" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Recent Developments (2022–2025)" title="Direct link to Recent Developments (2022–2025)">​</a></h3>
<p>In the last few years, LoRaWAN adoption has accelerated and diversified. As of the end of 2022, <a href="https://transformainsights.com/low-power-wide-area-networks#:~:text=Insights%20transformainsights,deployment%2C%20the%20focus%20of" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">industry analysts estimated over 200 million LoRaWAN devices were active worldwide</a>​. The LoRa Alliance’s 2022 report highlighted that LoRaWAN is no longer “new” but a widely adopted IoT technology, with deployments in 160+ countries and a rapidly growing ecosystem​. By 2023, the number of LoRaWAN network operators had nearly doubled to ~200 (from 100 in 2018), providing coverage <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/lora-alliance-press-release/lora-alliance-registra-una-crescita-del-66-delle-reti-pubbliche-lorawan-negli-ultimi-3-anni/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">“in nearly every country in the world”</a>​.</p>
<p>Analyst projections show LoRa/LoRaWAN connections continuing a steep rise: <a href="https://www.rcrwireless.com/20240619/internet-of-things/nb-iot-and-lorawan-crowned-the-kings-of-long-range-iot-to-double-connections-to-3-5bn-in-five-years#:~:text=judging%20by%20a%20cursory%20look,3%20million" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">around 500 million connections in 2024, expected to reach 1.3 billion by 2030</a>​. This growth is now driven not just by traditional public networks, but also by community and hybrid models. A notable phenomenon has been the Helium network, a community-built LoRaWAN network where individuals deploy hotspots. By 2022, Helium had over 800,000 LoRaWAN gateways worldwide contributing coverage​, although that has stabilized to around <a href="https://world.helium.com/en/iot/hotspots" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">300,000 gateways today</a> – a scale rivaling telecom operators. Another trend is LoRaWAN via satellite: since 2020, multiple operators (e.g. <a href="https://lacuna-space.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lacuna Space</a>, <a href="https://echostarmobile.com/lora-satellite-iot-devices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EchoStar</a>, <a href="https://www.eutelsat.com/en/blog/iot-connectivity-for-businesses.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eutelsat</a> have launched LoRaWAN-capable satellites, aiming for global IoT coverage for remote areas​. LoRaWAN protocol extensions now support satellite links and have opened use cases in maritime and wilderness monitoring.</p>
<p>Technologically, LoRaWAN has continued to improve. Newer device classes and features (<a href="https://www.semtech.com/uploads/technology/LoRa/lorawan-device-classes.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Class B for scheduled receive slots, Class C for near-continuous listening</a>) were implemented to support applications needing downlink or lower latency. Recent specifications have introduced relay nodes and network roaming to increase coverage and flexibility.</p>
<p>The focus has also turned to network scalability and management as deployments grew – demonstrated by initiatives like <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/actility.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LoRaWAN Network Roaming</a> across providers and the development of peering platforms (e.g. <a href="https://packetbroker.net/getting-started/what-is-packet-broker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Packet Broker</a>) to interconnect public and private LoRaWAN networks.</p>
<p>All these advancements show LoRaWAN’s evolution from a novel idea to a mature, global IoT standard with a decade of development. It now stands alongside cellular IoT options, offering a proven low-power, long-range connectivity solution with a robust ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="key-players-in-the-lorawan-ecosystem">Key Players in the LoRaWAN Ecosystem<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#key-players-in-the-lorawan-ecosystem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Players in the LoRaWAN Ecosystem" title="Direct link to Key Players in the LoRaWAN Ecosystem">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Semtech Corporation</strong> – Semtech is the semiconductor company that owns and licenses LoRa technology. It acquired French startup Cycleo (the inventor of LoRa’s radio modulation) in 2012 to <a href="https://blog.semtech.com/a-brief-history-of-lora-three-inventors-share-their-personal-story-at-the-things-conference#:~:text=Convinced%20about%20the%20long%20range,time%2C%20the%20creation%20of%20the" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">commercialize LoRa chips​</a>. Semtech produces the LoRa transceiver chips (e.g. SX1272/76) used in IoT devices and gateway chipsets (e.g. SX1301) that form the hardware backbone of LoRaWAN networks​. Semtech has been the key driver behind LoRa’s development and works closely with the <a href="https://www.lora-alliance.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LoRa Alliance</a>.</p>
<p><strong>The Things Industries (TTI)</strong> – <a href="https://www.thethingsindustries.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Things Industries</a> is the company behind The Things Network, a global open LoRaWAN community. Led by founders like Wienke Giezeman, TTI provides a LoRaWAN network server and infrastructure that power both community-driven and commercial deployments. The Things Network began in 2015 in the Netherlands as an open, crowdsourced LoRaWAN network and has grown worldwide. TTI is a leading provider of LoRaWAN solutions for enterprises, and a prominent member of the LoRa Alliance​.</p>
<p><strong>Actility</strong> – <a href="https://www.actility.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Actility</a> (founded by Olivier Hersent in 2010) is a French company and a pioneer in LPWAN connectivity platforms. Actility’s ThingPark platform is widely used for <a href="https://www.semtech.com/company/press/leading-iot-industry-players-bring-implementation-of-relay-utilizing-lorawan-to-market#:~:text=Actility%20is%20the%20world%20leader,Actility%20provides%20its" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">industrial-grade LoRaWAN network management​</a>. Many telecom operators launching LoRaWAN networks have partnered with Actility for core network servers. Actility is considered a world leader in LoRaWAN network solutions, enabling nationwide deployments and IoT services for smart cities, utilities, and industry​.</p>
<p><strong>Helium</strong> – <a href="https://www.helium.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Helium</a> is a blockchain-based network for the Internet of Things (IoT). It uses a crowdsourced network of LoRaWAN gateways to provide coverage for the internet of things. The Helium blockchain is used to reward gateways for contributing to the network.</p>
<p>Other Major Companies – The LoRaWAN ecosystem includes many players across hardware, network operations, and cloud services. Key contributors in the LoRa Alliance include <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LoRa#:~:text=Key%20contributing%20members%20of%20the,36" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">device manufacturers, network operators, and cloud giants</a>​. Notable examples are <a href="https://www.kerlink.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kerlink</a> (LoRaWAN gateway manufacturer), <a href="https://tektelic.com/products/gateways/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TEKTELIC</a> and <a href="https://mikrotik.com/products/group/iot-products" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MikroTik</a> (hardware providers), <a href="https://www.rcrwireless.com/20240207/internet-of-things/netmore-buys-senet-to-create-trans-atlantic-lorawan-operator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Netmore</a> which recently acquired Senet (a former LoRaWAN operator in the US), <a href="https://everynet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Everynet</a> (operates LoRaWAN networks internationally), and <a href="https://www.machineq.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MachineQ</a> (Comcast) – Comcast’s enterprise IoT arm offering LoRaWAN in the US​.</p>
<p>Cloud and tech companies like Amazon Web Services (<a href="https://aws.amazon.com/iot-core/lorawan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AWS IoT</a>) and <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/iot-hub/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Microsoft Azure</a> are also involved, providing IoT services that integrate LoRaWAN connectivity​. Even traditional telcos and tech firms such as Cisco were part of the ecosystem (Cisco provided LoRaWAN infrastructure gear, though it <a href="https://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/products/collateral/routers/wireless-gateway-lorawan/lorawan-eol.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">announced its exit</a> from this market in late 2024)​.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="notable-individuals-and-thought-leaders">Notable Individuals and Thought Leaders<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#notable-individuals-and-thought-leaders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Notable Individuals and Thought Leaders" title="Direct link to Notable Individuals and Thought Leaders">​</a></h2>
<p>The LoRaWAN industry was <a href="https://blog.semtech.com/a-brief-history-of-lora-three-inventors-share-their-personal-story-at-the-things-conference#:~:text=The%20story%20of%20LoRa%20began,the%20technology%20for%20sending%20data." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">kickstarted by inventors Nicolas Sornin and Olivier Seller</a>, who in 2009 first developed the long-range, chirp spread spectrum radio technology that became LoRa​. They co-founded Cycleo with François Sforza to target utility metering, which led to Semtech’s acquisition in 2012​. <a href="https://www.thethingsnetwork.org/article/nicolas-sornin-tells-about-the-future-of-lorawan" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nicolas Sornin</a> is often credited as the inventor of LoRa/LoRaWAN and continues to influence LoRaWAN’s evolution as an executive at Semtech.</p>
<p>On the ecosystem side, <a href="https://www.thethingsnetwork.org/u/wienkegiezeman" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wienke Giezeman</a> and <a href="https://www.thethingsnetwork.org/u/johan" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Johan Stokking</a> (The Things Network founders) are notable for mobilizing the global LoRaWAN community.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.actility.com/management-team/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Olivier Hersent</a> (Actility’s CEO) is a recognized expert who helped shape LoRaWAN’s early technical architecture. In the LoRa Alliance,former CEO <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/donnamoore4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Donna Moore</a> has been instrumental in driving global standardization and adoption while current CEO <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/author/alper-yeginlora-alliance-com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Alper Yegin</a>, appointed in October of 2024, has a track record indicating a strategic, forward-looking approach to ecosystem development.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/thomastelkamp/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thomas Telkamp</a>, CTO and co-foudner at Lacuna Space brought LoRaWAN into space, which was important because prior to this, if there wasn't a physical gateway on the ground, you weren't getting LoRaWAN coverage.</p>
<p>Other thought leaders include industry engineers like <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/olivier-seller-527909/?originalSubdomain=fr" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Olivier Seller</a> (Semtech) and ecosystem advocates such as <a href="https://www.techtarget.com/contributor/Marc-Pegulu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Marc Pégulu</a> (Semtech’s IoT VP) and <a href="https://x.com/amirhaleem" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Amir Haleem</a>, co-founder of <a href="https://www.helium.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Helium</a>, which used crowdsourcing to build the largest LoRaWAN network in the world.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dkjendal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dave Kjendal</a>, the former CTO at Senet and LoRa Alliance Technical Director and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dave-tholl-a31252a/?originalSubdomain=ca" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dave Tholl</a> at Tektelic have also contributed mightily to the LoRaWAN ecosystem.</p>
<p>These individuals, among others, have guided LoRaWAN from a niche technology to a global IoT standard.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lorawan-vs-other-lpwan-technologies">LoRaWAN vs. Other LPWAN Technologies<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#lorawan-vs-other-lpwan-technologies" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to LoRaWAN vs. Other LPWAN Technologies" title="Direct link to LoRaWAN vs. Other LPWAN Technologies">​</a></h2>
<p>LoRaWAN is one of several Low-Power Wide-Area Network (LPWAN) technologies addressing IoT connectivity.
The LPWAN field also includes cellular standards like NB-IoT and LTE-M, and proprietary systems like Sigfox, among others. Below is a brief comparison for context:</p>
<p><strong>LoRaWAN (LoRa Wide Area Network):</strong> An open LPWAN protocol operating in unlicensed ISM bands (e.g. 868 MHz in Europe, 915 MHz in US). LoRaWAN’s key advantages are its long range (15+ km in rural areas), very low power consumption, and an ecosystem not tied to any single operator – anyone can set up a LoRaWAN network. As a result, LoRaWAN supports private networks (enterprise or community) as well as public operator networks.</p>
<p>Globally, LoRa/LoRaWAN connections were estimated around 500 million in 2024, headed toward 1.3 billion by 2030​. LoRaWAN leads the LPWAN market in Europe and North America and is the top choice for private IoT deployments worldwide​. Its alliance-driven model means a multi-vendor ecosystem of devices, gateways, and software, giving users choice and often lower cost. The trade-off is that LoRaWAN operates in unlicensed spectrum, which has power and duty-cycle limits and potential interference (mitigated by adaptive data rates and robust modulation).</p>
<p><strong>NB-IoT (<a href="https://www.gsma.com/solutions-and-impact/technologies/internet-of-things/narrow-band-internet-of-things-nb-iot/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Narrowband IoT</a>):</strong> A LPWAN radio standard defined by 3GPP, operating in licensed cellular spectrum. NB-IoT is deployed by mobile carriers on their infrastructure. It offers similar low-data, long-battery capabilities as LoRaWAN, but with telco control. <a href="https://www.lightreading.com/iot/china-crosses-100m-nb-iot-connections-but-still-short-of-target" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NB-IoT has seen massive adoption in China</a> – about 90% of NB-IoT connections are in China​ thanks to strong government and operator backing. Globally, NB-IoT leads in total connections; as of 2024 NB-IoT had ~900 million connections (mostly in Asia), projected to reach ~1.9 billion by 2030​. LoRaWAN, by contrast, <a href="https://www.iot-now.com/2024/06/20/145050-nb-iot-and-lora-dominate-lpwan-market/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dominates in most regions outside China</a>​.</p>
<p>NB-IoT’s reliance on carriers means it’s used primarily for operator-driven public networks (e.g. <a href="https://stl.tech/blog/how-do-telcos-contribute-to-utilities-that-utilize-iot-technology/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">nationwide utility metering by telcos</a>). It generally offers slightly higher data rates than LoRaWAN and better integration with cellular networks, at the cost of higher infrastructure complexity and usually less flexibility for private deployments.</p>
<p><strong>Sigfox:</strong> <a href="https://www.sigfox.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sigfox</a> is a proprietary LPWAN technology (originating from a French startup of the same name) that also uses unlicensed sub-GHz spectrum but with a very narrow-band modulation. Sigfox networks are characterized by ultra-narrowband signals and a star topology with Sigfox-owned base stations. In the 2010s, Sigfox built out its own global network in dozens of countries.</p>
<p>Unlike LoRaWAN’s open multi-operator approach, Sigfox was a single-network, vertically integrated solution. Sigfox achieved some adoption (notably in France, Spain, and parts of Latin America) for simple sensors and tracking devices, but it faced challenges scaling. By end of 2023, <a href="https://www.rcrwireless.com/20240619/internet-of-things/nb-iot-and-lorawan-crowned-the-kings-of-long-range-iot-to-double-connections-to-3-5bn-in-five-years" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the installed base of Sigfox devices was only about 12.5 million</a>​ – far lower than LoRaWAN or NB-IoT. The Sigfox company filed for bankruptcy in 2022 and was acquired by Unabiz, which is now attempting to revive and open up the ecosystem​. Sigfox’s technical limits (very low message counts per day, no mesh or relay capabilities) and the business model of a single global operator hampered its growth relative to LoRaWAN’s flexible approach.</p>
<p><strong>LTE-M (Cat-M1):</strong> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LTE-M" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LTE-M</a> is a cellular IoT standard (also by 3GPP) that can be seen as the “twin” of NB-IoT, offering higher bandwidth and mobility (supporting device handover between cell towers) at the cost of higher power usage. It operates in licensed bands on LTE networks. LTE-M is often used for applications needing more data or voice (e.g. wearables or vehicle telematics), complementing NB-IoT. In LPWAN contexts, LTE-M has a smaller share: around 100+ million connections in 2024, forecast to reach ~400 million by 2030​.</p>
<p>LTE-M is popular in North America (operators like AT&amp;T, Verizon deployed LTE-M nationwide) and developed Asia (e.g. Japan) for IoT use cases that require the cellular network’s QoS and roaming. However, for the very low-power, low-cost sensor scenarios, LTE-M is less efficient than LoRaWAN or NB-IoT.</p>
<p>Other LPWANs: There are other niche or emerging LPWAN technologies. <strong>Wi-SUN</strong> (Wireless Smart Utility Network) is a mesh networking standard often used by utilities (especially in smart electricity metering) – it isn’t strictly long-range star network like LoRaWAN, but serves a similar market. <strong>MIoTy</strong> is a newer LPWAN protocol based on telegram-splitting (TS-UNB) technology, targeting industrial IoT with high interference tolerance. These technologies are still in early stages; collectively their deployments were around 20 million devices in 2024​, expected to grow to 100+ million by 2030. They target specific niches (Wi-SUN in utility grids, MIoTy in factory sensor networks, etc.), often inspired by the success of LoRaWAN’s open ecosystem model.</p>
<p>In summary, <a href="https://www.rcrwireless.com/20240619/internet-of-things/nb-iot-and-lorawan-crowned-the-kings-of-long-range-iot-to-double-connections-to-3-5bn-in-five-years#:~:text=NB,3%20million" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NB-IoT and LoRaWAN are the two dominant LPWAN technologies globally</a>, accounting for about 86% of LPWA connections today. NB-IoT holds the lead in absolute connections due to China’s massive deployments, but LoRaWAN is the leader in most other regions and in private IoT networks​. Sigfox, once a competitor, now lags far behind in scale​.</p>
<p>LoRaWAN’s openness, flexibility, and multi-vendor support have made it a preferred choice for many IoT projects, while NB-IoT is preferred when a licensed-band, operator-managed solution is required (especially by government mandate or where existing cellular infrastructure is leveraged). The two aren’t mutually exclusive – some IoT solutions use LoRaWAN for certain tasks and NB-IoT or LTE-M for others, and hybrid deployments are evolving. But broadly, the LPWAN landscape has settled into a duopoly of LoRaWAN and NB-IoT coexisting, with LoRaWAN excelling in unlicensed, collaborative deployments and NB-IoT in carrier-centric models​</p>
<h1>Global LPWAN Technology Analysis 2024</h1>
<table><thead><tr><th>Technology</th><th>Spectrum</th><th>Standard &amp; Ecosystem</th><th>Estimated Devices (2024)</th><th>Notable Regions and Uses</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>LoRaWAN</td><td>Unlicensed ISM (e.g. 868/915 MHz)</td><td>Open standard via LoRa Alliance; multi-vendor ecosystem (Semtech chips)</td><td>~500 million RCRWIRELESS.COM (projected to 1.3B by 2030)</td><td>Global (leader outside China) RCRWIRELESS.COM; used in smart cities, utilities, agriculture, logistics, private IoT networks.</td></tr><tr><td>NB-IoT</td><td>Licensed Cellular (e.g. LTE bands)</td><td>3GPP standard (cellular operators)</td><td>~900 million RCRWIRELESS.COM (projected ~1.9B by 2030)</td><td>Dominant in China (90% of connections) RCRWIRELESS.COM; growing in Europe, ME. Ideal for nationwide carrier-led deployments (smart meters, etc.).</td></tr><tr><td>Sigfox</td><td>Unlicensed ISM (Ultra-narrowband)</td><td>Proprietary (Sigfox/Unabiz network)</td><td>~12.5 million RCRWIRELESS.COM (2023)</td><td>Primarily Europe and LATAM; single operator model. Used for simple tracking and sensors. Slower growth due to proprietary model.</td></tr><tr><td>LTE-M (Cat-M1)</td><td>Licensed Cellular (LTE)</td><td>3GPP standard (cellular operators)</td><td>100+ million RCRWIRELESS.COM</td><td>North America, Japan, etc. Suited for IoT needing higher bandwidth or mobility (wearables, vehicles). Often paired with NB-IoT deployments.</td></tr><tr><td>Others (Wi-SUN, MIoTy)</td><td>Unlicensed (sub-GHz)</td><td>Wi-SUN Alliance; MIoTy Alliance (ETSI TS-UNB)</td><td>~20 million RCRWIRELESS.COM (combined 2024)</td><td>Emerging tech: Wi-SUN in smart utility grids; MIoTy in industrial sensor networks. Growing niche adoption.</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.rcrwireless.com/20240619/internet-of-things/nb-iot-and-lorawan-crowned-the-kings-of-long-range-iot-to-double-connections-to-3-5bn-in-five-years#:~:text=Meanwhile%2C%20high,the%20graph%20to%20be%20limited" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RCR Wireless News, 2024</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="market-analysis">Market Analysis<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#market-analysis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Market Analysis" title="Direct link to Market Analysis">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="regional-adoption-and-investment">Regional Adoption and Investment<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#regional-adoption-and-investment" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Regional Adoption and Investment" title="Direct link to Regional Adoption and Investment">​</a></h3>
<p>LoRaWAN has achieved global reach, but adoption varies by region. Europe was an early adopter and remains a stronghold of LoRaWAN deployment. By 2020, <a href="https://www.industryarc.com/Report/19424/lora-and-lorawan-devices-market.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Europe accounted for about 36.4%</a> of the global LoRa/LoRaWAN devices market – the largest share at the time​. European countries embraced LoRaWAN early for national networks and city projects.</p>
<p><strong>France</strong> not only saw its major telcos deploy LoRaWAN nationwide, but also has millions of devices in operation. France alone has <a href="https://resources.lora-alliance.org/home/lorawan-deployments-achieve-market-leadership-deliver-strong-roi-for-iot-across-wide-spectrum-of-industries-across-france-and-spain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">over 1.5 million LoRaWAN devices deployed</a> as of 2022​, including applications like smart water meters and environmental sensors. The Spanish government <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/category/lora-alliance-press-release/page/5/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">plans to deploy 13.5 million smart water meters by 2025</a> (a €1.35 billion project), many of which will use LoRaWAN for connectivity​ – a testament to the country’s investment in this tech for utilities. <strong>Spain</strong> is a leading market in Europe, with about 500,000 LoRaWAN devices active (and 200k more being added) as of 2022​. Countries like the Netherlands, Belgium, Switzerland, and Germany also host nationwide or wide-scale LoRaWAN networks, often led by telecom operators or regional utility collaborations.</p>
<p><strong>North America</strong> has become a major growth region for LoRaWAN in recent years. The United States in particular has seen wide adoption of private LoRaWAN networks in enterprise and industrial contexts, as well as community deployments. <a href="https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2024/09/10/2943901/0/en/LoRa-and-LoRaWAN-IoT-Market-Is-Expected-To-Reach-a-Revenue-Of-USD-183-9-Bn-By-2033-At-36-5-CAGR-Dimension-Market-Research.html#:~:text=Regional%20Analysis-,North%20America%20is%20projected%20to%20dominate%20the%20global%20LoRa%20and,supporting%20large%2Dscale%20IoT%20deployments." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Market reports</a> indicate North America is now the leading region by LoRaWAN market revenue, with about 40.1% of global LoRa/LoRaWAN market share in 2024​.</p>
<p>This leadership is driven by large-scale deployments in sectors like smart agriculture (e.g. connected irrigation in California), logistics (asset tracking in supply chains), and smart buildings. Several dedicated LoRaWAN network operators have emerged in the US, such as Senet (covering many regions with public LoRaWAN service) and MachineQ (Comcast) providing LoRaWAN for enterprise campuses. Moreover, the <strong>Helium</strong> community network – with over 800k crowd-funded hotspots across North America and beyond – has effectively blanketed many urban areas with LoRaWAN coverage​.</p>
<p>This combination of commercial and community initiatives has attracted significant investment into LoRaWAN-based solutions in the U.S. and Canada. (In Canada, cities like Calgary and companies in mining/oil industries are using LoRaWAN for remote monitoring). North America’s momentum is further boosted by cloud integration; e.g., Amazon’s <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/iot-core/lorawan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AWS IoT Core supports LoRaWAN devices</a>, making it easier for businesses to adopt the technology.</p>
<p><strong>Asia-Pacific</strong> presents a mixed landscape due to the prominence of NB-IoT in some countries.</p>
<p><strong>China</strong>, by policy, focused on NB-IoT (with tens of millions of NB-IoT smart meters deployed), so LoRaWAN’s public footprint in China is relatively small. However, LoRa is used in China in private industrial networks and by some regional carriers for specific verticals. Outside China, LoRaWAN has seen strong uptake in Asia.</p>
<p><strong>South Korea</strong> was one of the first APAC countries to invest heavily – SK Telecom’s nationwide LoRaWAN network (launched 2016) was used for services from metering to manhole monitoring​.</p>
<p><strong>India</strong> has a <a href="https://www.tatacommunications.com/press-release/hpe-work-tata-communications-build-worlds-largest-iot-network-india-enhance-resource-utilization/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">large LoRaWAN network rolled out</a> by Tata Communications covering dozens of cities, supporting use cases like smart street lighting, agriculture, and asset tracking. In <strong>Japan</strong>, telecom operators and big tech firms (e.g. SoftBank, NEC) have run LoRaWAN trials and deployments for smart city systems. <strong>Australia</strong> and <strong>New Zealand</strong> have active LoRaWAN communities and regional networks (often targeting agriculture in remote areas). Generally, Asia-Pacific is seen as the fastest-growing LoRaWAN market, as IoT adoption surges across Southeast Asia and India​.</p>
<p>The absence of ubiquitous NB-IoT in some emerging economies gives LoRaWAN an opportunity to be the connectivity of choice for IoT projects, which is reflected in increasing investments there.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="other-regions">Other Regions:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#other-regions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Other Regions:" title="Direct link to Other Regions:">​</a></h3>
<p>In <strong>Latin America</strong>, LoRaWAN has gained traction in countries like Brazil, Mexico, and Argentina for smart agriculture and city applications. For example, Brazil has LoRaWAN networks used in agri-tech (connecting farm sensors over long ranges).</p>
<p><strong>Mexico City</strong> has pilot projects for air quality monitoring on LoRaWAN. Many LATAM deployments have been spearheaded by local telcos in partnership with LoRaWAN solution providers.</p>
<p>In the Middle East and Africa, IoT adoption is still emerging, but LoRaWAN is present in several countries. <strong>South Africa</strong> has seen LoRaWAN used in wildlife conservation and utility metering pilots.</p>
<p>The United Arab Emirates and <a href="https://saudiex.com.sa/what-is-lorawan/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Saudi Arabia have smart city initiatives</a> where LoRaWAN is evaluated for connecting municipal sensors. One advantage in developing regions is LoRaWAN’s low cost and flexibility (no need for licensed spectrum), making it attractive for NGOs and city authorities to deploy networks for specific needs (like disaster warning sensors, agricultural soil monitoring, etc.). The LoRa Alliance notes that as of 2020, LoRaWAN networks (public or private) are active in over 160 countries worldwide, indicating a truly global spread.</p>
<p>To support this growth, over 160 major mobile network operators (MNOs) have deployed LoRaWAN networks or services globally​. This is a remarkable number, showing that many of the same telecom companies that run cellular networks also invest in LoRaWAN as part of their IoT portfolio. Examples include Orange, SK Telecom, KPN, Swisscom, Deutsche Telekom (via subsidiary), Comcast, Telstra, and Tata Communications, among many others. This broad backing by operators and enterprises ensures continuing investment into LoRaWAN infrastructure in virtually every region.</p>
<p>(For a snapshot of key LoRaWAN markets, see Table 2.)</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="table-2-selected-lorawan-adoption-highlights-by-countryregion">Table 2: Selected LoRaWAN Adoption Highlights by Country/Region<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#table-2-selected-lorawan-adoption-highlights-by-countryregion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Table 2: Selected LoRaWAN Adoption Highlights by Country/Region" title="Direct link to Table 2: Selected LoRaWAN Adoption Highlights by Country/Region">​</a></h2>
<table><thead><tr><th>Country/Region</th><th>LoRaWAN Adoption Highlights</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>France</td><td>Two nationwide networks (Orange &amp; Bouygues) since 2016; &gt;1.5 million devices on LoRaWAN to date MOKOLORA.COM. Major projects in utilities (e.g. plan for 13.5M smart water meters by 2025) MOKOLORA.COM and smart cities. Paris and other cities use LoRaWAN for street lighting, parking sensors, and environmental monitoring.</td></tr><tr><td>United States</td><td>Mix of public and private deployments; no single nationwide network, but regional coverage by operators like Senet and community Helium network (~800k gateways) BLOG.LORA-ALLIANCE.ORG. Used in industrial IoT (oil &amp; gas, manufacturing), agriculture (crop monitoring in California), and logistics (asset tracking by logistics firms). Comcast's MachineQ and Everynet provide LoRaWAN in many metro areas. Strong enterprise uptake due to easy private network setup.</td></tr><tr><td>Netherlands</td><td>Early adopter – KPN launched one of the first national LoRaWAN networks in 2016 SDXCENTRAL.COM. Also home to The Things Network, which started in Amsterdam and spread community LoRaWAN across Europe. LoRaWAN used in smart agriculture (e.g. soil sensors in fields) and flood control (dike monitoring sensors) by Dutch water authorities.</td></tr><tr><td>India</td><td>Tata Communications deployed LoRaWAN across ~38 cities by 2017, creating one of the largest LoRa networks in Asia. Focus on smart city use cases: connected streetlights, waste management, and soil moisture sensors for farmers. Indian startups and system integrators have embraced LoRaWAN for its cost-effectiveness in rural IoT projects.</td></tr><tr><td>South Korea</td><td>SK Telecom completed a nationwide LoRaWAN network in 2016 SAMSUNG.COM, parallel to its LTE-M rollout. LoRaWAN is used for city services in Seoul and other areas: e.g. monitoring public infrastructure (manholes, streetlights) and providing connectivity for thousands of gas and water meters. South Korea's case proved the feasibility of large-scale LoRaWAN by a mobile operator.</td></tr><tr><td>Spain</td><td>Rapid growth in LoRaWAN deployments; ~500,000 devices live on LoRaWAN (2022) MOKOLORA.COM, with more being added for smart utility and tracking projects. Cities like Barcelona and Madrid use LoRaWAN for smart parking and environmental sensing. Spanish telecoms (Telefónica, Everynet in partnership) have nationwide LoRaWAN coverage.</td></tr><tr><td>Australia</td><td>Strong adoption in mining and agriculture. Several regional networks cover farming areas (for water tank monitoring, cattle tracking). The national science agency CSIRO has trialed LoRaWAN for environmental monitoring in the outback due to its long range. Major cities have community LoRaWAN coverage via The Things Network.</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>(Note: The above table highlights a few examples; LoRaWAN is present in many more countries worldwide, often with multiple networks per country.)</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="major-use-cases-and-industries">Major Use Cases and Industries<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#major-use-cases-and-industries" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Major Use Cases and Industries" title="Direct link to Major Use Cases and Industries">​</a></h2>
<p>LoRaWAN’s versatility and low operating cost have led to its use across a wide range of industries. The LoRa Alliance identifies six key vertical domains driving LoRaWAN adoption: Smart Agriculture, Smart Buildings, Smart Cities, Smart Industry (manufacturing), Smart Logistics, and Smart Utilities​. In each of these, LoRaWAN enables new IoT solutions that were previously impractical with shorter-range or higher-power networks. Below we outline these major use cases and examples:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="smart-utilities-watergaselectric-metering">Smart Utilities (Water/Gas/Electric Metering):<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#smart-utilities-watergaselectric-metering" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Smart Utilities (Water/Gas/Electric Metering):" title="Direct link to Smart Utilities (Water/Gas/Electric Metering):">​</a></h3>
<p>Utility metering is a flagship LoRaWAN application. Utilities deploy LoRaWAN-enabled smart water meters and gas meters to collect readings remotely over long distances. The long battery life (often 10+ years) of LoRaWAN meters and deep indoor penetration make it ideal for this use. For example, cities in France are rolling out millions of LoRaWAN water meters to automate usage readings and detect leaks in real-time​.</p>
<p>In Spain, LoRaWAN is used by utilities for gas meter monitoring (replacing manual monthly checks). Electricity grid operators also use LoRaWAN for grid telemetry in some regions. <a href="https://www.digi.com/blog/post/calculating-roi-for-lorawan-deployments" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The ROI is significant</a> – automated meter reading saves labor and can reduce water loss by early leak detection, yielding economic and environmental benefits. Utilities also use LoRaWAN for smart grid sensors (e.g. monitoring distribution transformers or pole top monitors in electric networks).</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="smart-cities">Smart Cities:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#smart-cities" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Smart Cities:" title="Direct link to Smart Cities:">​</a></h3>
<p>Urban deployments of LoRaWAN cover a broad array of smart city services. Street lighting control is commonly done via LoRaWAN nodes that allow dimming schedules and maintenance alerts (achieving energy savings for municipalities). Smart parking systems use LoRa sensors embedded in parking spots to relay availability, reducing traffic congestion.</p>
<p>Cities like Los Angeles, Amsterdam, and Singapore have trialed such solutions. Waste management is another use: LoRaWAN bin sensors report fill levels so that trash collection routes can be optimized (as done in cities in Belgium and Australia). Environmental monitoring is also crucial – many cities deploy LoRaWAN air quality sensors and noise sensors on street poles to gather hyperlocal pollution data.</p>
<p>The cost-effectiveness of LoRaWAN (no monthly SIM fees, one gateway can cover a whole district) makes these city-wide sensor networks feasible within municipal budgets. <a href="https://www.smartcitiesworld.net/internet-of-things/simplifying-the-smart-city" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">There are numerous examples globally of cities achieving strong ROI</a> and improved services with LoRaWAN deployments in lighting, parking, and waste management (e.g., improved parking fee collection, lower energy bills, etc.)​. LoRaWAN’s presence in smart cities continues to grow as part of “Smart City” initiatives.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="smart-agriculture">Smart Agriculture:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#smart-agriculture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Smart Agriculture:" title="Direct link to Smart Agriculture:">​</a></h3>
<p>Agriculture and farming benefit from LoRaWAN by enabling IoT in fields far from cellular coverage. Soil moisture sensors, weather stations, and crop health sensors with LoRaWAN connectivity help farmers do precision agriculture – irrigating only when needed, optimizing fertilizer use, and monitoring microclimates. LoRaWAN collars or tags on livestock (cattle, sheep) enable ranchers to track animal location and health across large pastures.</p>
<p>In Australia and the US, <a href="https://www.ndsu.edu/agriculture/extension/publications/basics-lora-technology-crop-and-livestock-management" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ranchers use LoRaWAN to get alerts if cattle wander or if water levels in remote tanks are low</a>. These devices run on small batteries or solar and can transmit miles to the nearest gateway. The economic impact is notable: improved yields and reduced resource waste.</p>
<p>In wine regions (like California and Italy), vineyards use LoRaWAN sensors to monitor soil and vine conditions, leading to better crop management. Asia-Pacific’s fast LoRaWAN growth is partly due to agricultural use in countries like India and Indonesia, where rural connectivity is crucial​. The ability to cover large, remote areas with minimal infrastructure (just a few gateways covering thousands of acres) is a unique advantage of LoRaWAN in this sector.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="logistics-and-asset-tracking">Logistics and Asset Tracking:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#logistics-and-asset-tracking" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Logistics and Asset Tracking:" title="Direct link to Logistics and Asset Tracking:">​</a></h3>
<p>LoRaWAN is increasingly used for tracking assets that move through supply chains or within large facilities. LoRaWAN asset trackers (small battery-powered GPS or BLE-enabled tags) can be placed on pallets, containers, or equipment. They periodically send their location (or sensor data like temperature for cold-chain monitoring) to nearby LoRaWAN gateways. Logistics providers utilize LoRaWAN at ports and warehouses to track containers without needing cellular on each device. The range allows coverage of entire shipping yards with one gateway.</p>
<p>For cross-country or international tracking, LoRaWAN can be combined with satellite connectivity – for instance, a container tracker might use LoRaWAN to talk to a small satellite modem which then sends data back to the cloud​.</p>
<p>Companies have reported improved inventory management and theft reduction by using LoRaWAN trackers on high-value assets. In airports, luggage carts and equipment are tracked via private LoRaWAN networks (e.g. <a href="https://www.iotm2mcouncil.org/iot-library/news/smart-building-construction-news/kerlink-flies-lora-network-at-schiphol-airport/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Schiphol Airport in Amsterdam deployed a LoRaWAN network</a> for asset tracking over its campus​). The logistics sector values LoRaWAN for its low power (trackers can last years on a battery) and its ability to penetrate indoor areas like warehouses or basements where GPS alone fails.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="industrial-iot-smart-industry">Industrial IoT (Smart Industry):<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#industrial-iot-smart-industry" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Industrial IoT (Smart Industry):" title="Direct link to Industrial IoT (Smart Industry):">​</a></h3>
<p>Manufacturing plants and industrial sites use LoRaWAN for wireless monitoring of equipment and environment. Predictive maintenance is a key use: LoRaWAN vibration or temperature sensors on machines can regularly report data to predict failures. Because running cables in factories is expensive and Wi-Fi may not cover large sites, LoRaWAN provides a reliable, low-cost wireless backbone for these sensors. Safety monitoring is another aspect – LoRaWAN can connect gas leak detectors, fire alarms, or worker safety wearables throughout facilities.</p>
<p>In oil and gas fields, <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/LoRaWAN-OIl-Gas.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LoRaWAN connects pressure sensors and valve monitors</a> over wide areas. The manufacturing sector is projected to account for about 28% of LoRaWAN’s market in 2024​, underlining how important industrial use is. By retrofitting factories with LoRaWAN sensors, operators can reduce downtime (through early fault detection) and optimize processes, which has direct financial benefits.</p>
<p>A factory might <a href="https://akenza.io/blog/retrofitting-energy-meters-with-lora" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">use LoRaWAN energy meters on equipment</a> to identify power hogs and cut electricity costs – a simple IoT retrofit made feasible by the ease of LoRaWAN wireless deployment.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="smart-buildings">Smart Buildings:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#smart-buildings" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Smart Buildings:" title="Direct link to Smart Buildings:">​</a></h3>
<p>In commercial real estate and facility management, LoRaWAN is used to make buildings “smart” at a low cost. Heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems are instrumented with LoRaWAN temperature and humidity sensors in different rooms to optimize climate control. Occupancy sensors and people counters using LoRaWAN help manage meeting room usage or lighting (lights can be automated to turn off when areas are unoccupied). Indoor air quality sensors (for CO₂, VOCs) on LoRaWAN are deployed in offices and schools to ensure healthy ventilation.</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-tip admonition_xJq3 alert alert--success"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 12 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.5 0C3.48 0 1 2.19 1 5c0 .92.55 2.25 1 3 1.34 2.25 1.78 2.78 2 4v1h5v-1c.22-1.22.66-1.75 2-4 .45-.75 1-2.08 1-3 0-2.81-2.48-5-5.5-5zm3.64 7.48c-.25.44-.47.8-.67 1.11-.86 1.41-1.25 2.06-1.45 3.23-.02.05-.02.11-.02.17H5c0-.06 0-.13-.02-.17-.2-1.17-.59-1.83-1.45-3.23-.2-.31-.42-.67-.67-1.11C2.44 6.78 2 5.65 2 5c0-2.2 2.02-4 4.5-4 1.22 0 2.36.42 3.22 1.19C10.55 2.94 11 3.94 11 5c0 .66-.44 1.78-.86 2.48zM4 14h5c-.23 1.14-1.3 2-2.5 2s-2.27-.86-2.5-2z"></path></svg></span>Want to build your own LoRaWAN dashboard?</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>Check out our <a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/docs/tutorial-extras/metsci-demo-dash">MetSci Demo Dashboard</a> to learn how to build a custom dashboard for monitoring your LoRaWAN sensors.</p></div></div>
<p>Building managers increasingly adopt LoRaWAN because a single gateway per building can connect hundreds of sensors through walls on multiple floors – something hard to do with Wi-Fi or Bluetooth.</p>
<p>LoRaWAN also excels in connecting <a href="https://lora-alliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/LA_WhitePaper_BACnet_1021_Final.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">elevator or basement equipment monitoring</a> that might be out of normal network range. The result is improved energy efficiency (some smart buildings report double-digit percentage reductions in energy use) and better facility utilization. With new LoRaWAN 2.4 GHz options and emerging standards, even more consumer and building devices might integrate LoRaWAN, and this domain is expected to grow.</p>
<p>Across all these sectors, LoRaWAN’s common value proposition is enabling data collection from many distributed points at low cost, with devices that can run for years on a battery. This has led to significant economic impacts: cost savings (e.g. in meter reading and maintenance), new revenue streams (IoT services offered by operators), and improved outcomes (e.g. higher crop yields, reduced city traffic).</p>
<p>As an illustration, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2772375522000181" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a study of LoRaWAN in precision agriculture</a> might find yield improvements of 5-10% for certain crops due to better irrigation control – which is economically very significant for farmers. In cities, smarter lighting can cut electricity costs by 30-50% in streetlight operations. While exact ROI varies by project, many markets are seeing high ROI from LoRaWAN deployments, which drives further investment. The collaborative ecosystem (sensor makers, network providers, software platforms) lowers barriers for new solutions, accelerating IoT innovation.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="emerging-trends-and-future-outlook">Emerging Trends and Future Outlook<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#emerging-trends-and-future-outlook" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Emerging Trends and Future Outlook" title="Direct link to Emerging Trends and Future Outlook">​</a></h2>
<p>The global LoRaWAN industry continues to evolve with new trends that will shape its future trajectory:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="satellite-enabled-lorawan">Satellite-Enabled LoRaWAN:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#satellite-enabled-lorawan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Satellite-Enabled LoRaWAN:" title="Direct link to Satellite-Enabled LoRaWAN:">​</a></h3>
<p>One of the most exciting developments is the expansion of LoRaWAN beyond terrestrial limits via satellite connectivity. Starting around 2020, several companies have launched low-earth-orbit satellites equipped to forward LoRaWAN messages​. This effectively creates a space-based LoRaWAN layer for truly global coverage – reaching remote oil rigs, ocean buoys, wildlife trackers, or any sensor outside of cell range. By 2022, early LoRaWAN satellite services (from firms like Lacuna, EchoStar, and Fossa) were in testing, and by 2023 some became commercially available.</p>
<p>This trend means LoRaWAN could unify terrestrial and satellite IoT on one standard, which is a unique advantage (NB-IoT and others are also pursuing satellite integration, but LoRa’s low power makes it well-suited to burst data to satellites). We can expect growth in hybrid devices that use terrestrial LoRaWAN when available and satellite when not, especially for asset tracking across land/sea and environmental monitoring in remote regions​.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="community-and-decentralized-networks">Community and Decentralized Networks:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#community-and-decentralized-networks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Community and Decentralized Networks:" title="Direct link to Community and Decentralized Networks:">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Helium’s</strong>* model of a decentralized, blockchain-incentivized LoRaWAN network sparked interest in new business models. By rewarding individuals for deploying coverage, Helium rapidly scaled the number of LoRaWAN gateways worldwide​. While the long-term viability of the crypto incentive is still evolving, the concept of community-driven networks is here to stay.</p>
<p>Other initiatives and community networks (like The Things Network community and regional IoT cooperatives) continue to expand coverage in areas perhaps underserved by traditional telcos. This trend could lead to a patchwork of public, private, and community networks that interoperate.</p>
<p>The LoRa Alliance is fostering roaming and data exchange between networks via standards like LoRaWAN roaming and the <a href="https://www.thethingsindustries.com/docs/concepts/packet-broker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Packet Broker</a>​, so that a device might seamlessly use any available LoRaWAN gateway regardless of owner. The blending of public, private, and community networks is a trend that increases overall coverage and resilience of the LoRaWAN ecosystem.</p>
<p>Convergence with 5G and Cellular IoT: Rather than viewing cellular IoT (NB-IoT/LTE-M) and LoRaWAN as purely competitors, the industry is exploring synergies. Hybrid solutions are emerging where LoRaWAN handles local low-power sensor data, and cellular or 5G backhaul carries aggregated data. For example, some gateway devices combine LoRaWAN and 4G/5G modems to forward data from LoRa sensors to cloud services.</p>
<p>There are also cases of operators <a href="https://univ-rennes.hal.science/hal-04239515/file/Jradi%20et%20al-2023-A%20Seamless%20Integration%20Solution%20for%20LoRaWAN%20Into%205G%20System.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">integrating LoRaWAN into their 5G networks as a slice</a> or offering managed LoRaWAN service along with NB-IoT. The fact that LoRaWAN leads in private networks has inspired the 5G community to develop private 5G/NR solutions – but those remain costly and power-hungry for many IoT needs.</p>
<p>We are likely to see LoRaWAN continue to fill the niche for ultra-low-power, long-range sensing even in a 5G world, often working in tandem with high-bandwidth technologies (e.g., using LoRaWAN for short messages and 5G for video or large data when needed). Semtech’s recent collaborations (e.g., with TTI and AWS) also indicate an effort to simplify IoT by uniting LoRaWAN connectivity with cloud platforms for device management​.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="growth-of-lorawan-ecosystem-and-new-standards">Growth of LoRaWAN Ecosystem and New Standards:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#growth-of-lorawan-ecosystem-and-new-standards" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Growth of LoRaWAN Ecosystem and New Standards:" title="Direct link to Growth of LoRaWAN Ecosystem and New Standards:">​</a></h2>
<p>The LoRaWAN ecosystem is maturing, with over 500 members in the LoRa Alliance and a proliferation of certified devices. Interoperability and certification ensure that sensors and gateways from different vendors work together, which will remain a focus.</p>
<p>As the ecosystem grows, we see new profiles (like LoRaWAN for smart homes, which might require interoperability with consumer IoT standards) and possibly lightweight versions for simpler devices. Also notable is the <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10614081" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">emergence of LoRaWAN in the 2.4 GHz band</a> (a globally available ISM band).</p>
<p>While most LoRaWAN today operates in sub-GHz regional bands, 2.4GHz LoRaWAN could allow a single device model to be used worldwide (trading off some range). This could open LoRaWAN to new consumer applications or worldwide logistics tracking without regional SKUs. The alliance-driven approach of LoRaWAN has been highlighted as a key to its success, and even other LPWAN groups (Wi-SUN, mioty) are following similar multi-stakeholder models​.</p>
<p>We can expect the Alliance to continue updating the standard (security enhancements, support for new frequency regulations, etc.) and driving collaborations (e.g., liaison with 3GPP for coexistence, with Wi-SUN alliance, etc.).</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="higher-density-and-scalability-solutions">Higher Density and Scalability Solutions:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#higher-density-and-scalability-solutions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Higher Density and Scalability Solutions:" title="Direct link to Higher Density and Scalability Solutions:">​</a></h3>
<p>As LoRaWAN networks grow from a handful of gateways to thousands (especially in dense urban deployments or massive industrial complexes), managing interference and capacity is a challenge. The industry is working on network optimization techniques like dynamic channel plans, interference mitigation, and perhaps future revisions of the protocol to allow even greater device densities.</p>
<p>Research and field experience are defining the limits of LoRaWAN capacity and how to push them (some studies show tens of thousands of devices can coexist per gateway under proper configurations). The introduction of repeating/relay nodes (an optional new feature) can extend range in tough radio environments, though with careful duty cycle management. All these efforts aim to ensure LoRaWAN can scale to the billions of devices projected in coming years.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="economic-impact-and-roi-focus">Economic Impact and ROI Focus:<a href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/03/Global_LoRaWAN_Industry_Analysis#economic-impact-and-roi-focus" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Economic Impact and ROI Focus:" title="Direct link to Economic Impact and ROI Focus:">​</a></h3>
<p>As deployments scale, customers are increasingly measuring the direct economic impact of LoRaWAN solutions. This feedback loop influences the market by highlighting successful applications. For example, if a city reports that its LoRaWAN smart lighting project paid for itself in energy savings within two years, other cities will quickly follow.</p>
<p>We are seeing such ROI-positive case studies accumulate in domains like smart metering (where utilities see reduced operating costs and improved revenue assurance by catching leaks/theft), cold chain monitoring (preventing spoilage of food or vaccines), and predictive maintenance (avoiding costly downtime in factories). These demonstrated successes drive further investment in LoRaWAN projects.</p>
<p>Industry analysts note that LoRaWAN’s multi-year head start in real-world deployments has <a href="https://www.nist.gov/system/files/documents/2024/10/21/The%20IoT%20of%20Things%20Oct%202024%20508%20FINAL_1.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">given it a credibility and “proof of concept”</a> library that newer technologies lack​. Consequently, the market is reaching a tipping point where IoT solution buyers trust LoRaWAN as a stable, cost-effective choice with proven outcomes, which should sustain its growth.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the global LoRaWAN industry has moved into a phase of mass adoption and diversification. Key players from startup innovators to telecom giants are collectively strengthening the ecosystem.</p>
<p>The technology has a rich history from 2009 to now, evolving from a French lab idea to an ITU-recognized international standard. When compared to other LPWANs, LoRaWAN stands out for its global community and flexibility, which has translated into it leading in most markets outside of China.</p>
<p>The market analysis shows healthy growth across continents, with particularly strong investment in Europe and North America and rapid expansion in Asia and beyond. LoRaWAN’s use cases now cover virtually every industry that needs IoT, delivering tangible benefits and ROI in each.</p>
<p>The data and trends indicate a robust trajectory: estimates of billions of LoRaWAN devices in the next decade​ and continued innovation (like satellite LoRaWAN and new standards) suggest that LoRaWAN will remain a cornerstone of the IoT landscape. Its ability to provide low-power, long-range connectivity at low cost addresses a fundamental IoT need, ensuring that the LoRaWAN industry will thrive as the Internet of Things continues its global growth.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="global" term="global"/>
        <category label="ttn" term="ttn"/>
        <category label="actility" term="actility"/>
        <category label="semtech" term="semtech"/>
        <category label="helium" term="helium"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Networked Synesthesia]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/02/Networked_Synesthesia</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/02/02/Networked_Synesthesia"/>
        <updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Synethesia is when the expereince of one sense triggers another.  The classic example is seeing colors when hearing music, but you could taste words, smell sounds, or feel textures when you see colors.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Synethesia is when the expereince of one sense triggers another.  The classic example is seeing colors when hearing music, but you could taste words, smell sounds, or feel textures when you see colors.</p>
<p>A recent excellent <a href="https://freakonomics.com/podcast/feeling-sound-and-hearing-color/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Freakonomics episode with David Eagleman</a> sparked an idea on how to combine synthestia with LoRaWAN for spatial awareness in the military context.</p>
<p>Dr. Eagleman described the develpment of the NeoSensory vest that captured sound and converted it to vibratory feedback on the torso, allowing deaf people to hear. We're all bathed in sound, but deafness is the inability to translate it into, well, sounds we hear.</p>
<p>By placing vibratory motors through a vest and then translating sounds into a felt experience, the brains of the users "livewired" themselves to hear sound again.  Pretty rad.</p>
<p>Dr. Eagleman managed to get that down from a vest to a bracelet with vibratory motors evenly spaced around the bracelet.  Interestingly, where a vibration is felt can be shifted between 2 motors by changing the power of the buzz in each motor.  The stronger the buzz (comparatively), the closer to that motor the sensation is felt.  This effectively gave them way more "buzz points" which translated into a more granular ability to translate incomin sound waves into signals the brain could use.</p>
<p>Now, if you can hear sounds with a bracelet, it's reasonable to imagine that you could get a sense of other things, including spatial awareness of where other people are if they're transmitting their position.</p>
<p>LoRa is a potential excellent wireless protocol for this; it's robust, low energy, can be encrypted (or could run through <a href="https://reticulum.network/?" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reticulum</a> so it's definitely encrypted, and long range (that's what LoRa is short for).</p>
<p>Imagine an element of soldiers all wearing a bracelet (or vest, or whatever) who could literally feel where other soldiers in their element were?</p>
<p>Obviously this could be used by firefighters and other rescue elements in chaotic situations.</p>
<p>By running this over LoRa (or a LoRaWAN) and integrating Reticulum to use multiple communications protocols and integrate other assets (an overhead drone with a LoRaWAN gateway, for example), you could potentially have an extraordinary advantage over a wide area whenever you need to coordinate human activity.</p>
<p>Pretty cool use case, eh?  Keep on crushing out there, and if you need help with IoT sensors, whether it's designed, deployment, or business-fit, please reach out.</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>Author</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p><strong>Nik Hawks</strong> is a LoRaWAN Educator &amp; Builder at <a href="https://meteoscientific.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MeteoScientific</a>. He writes to educate and delight people considering IoT, and to inspire other IoT nerds to build and deploy their own projects into the world. He runs a <a href="https://pod.metsci.show/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcast</a> discussing all things LoRaWAN and is psyched to hear about what you're building, whether it's a one sensor playground or a million sensor rollout.</p></div></div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="government" term="government"/>
        <category label="military" term="military"/>
        <category label="networking" term="networking"/>
        <category label="synesthesia" term="synesthesia"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How the U.S. Government Uses LoRaWAN]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/01/20/How_the_US_Government_Uses_LoRaWAN</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2025/01/20/How_the_US_Government_Uses_LoRaWAN"/>
        <updated>2025-01-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back in 2022, Mike Harttree, an IoT Architect at Cisco, gave a talk at the LoRa Alliance's annual conference about how the U.S. government is using LoRaWAN to enhance operational efficiency and tackle long-standing logistical challenges.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in 2022, Mike Harttree, an IoT Architect at Cisco, <a href="https://youtu.be/Gglwe9sKpCA?si=9IS_YBpHCynIk2dT" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">gave a talk at the LoRa Alliance's annual conference</a> about how the U.S. government is using LoRaWAN to enhance operational efficiency and tackle long-standing logistical challenges.</p>
<p>With all the current fuss about Meshtastic and LoRa, I thought it'd be a good idea to review what has already been done.  Some of this is super basic (replacing fuel stick measurements with digital ones), but after all, that's what IoT is about; digitizing the measurements of our world.</p>
<p>It doesn't have to be fancy, it just has to work.</p>
<p><strong>Introduction</strong><br>
<!-- -->The U.S. government has begun leveraging LoRaWAN technology to enhance operational efficiency and tackle long-standing logistical challenges. In a recent talk, Cisco's U.S. government IoT engineer detailed how LoRaWAN solutions are addressing critical needs in areas like military aviation and asset tracking. Here's a summary of how LoRaWAN is making an impact.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Cisco's Role in the LoRaWAN Ecosystem</strong><br>
<!-- -->Cisco has positioned itself as a significant player in the LoRaWAN space, with over 480 global customers deploying their gateways, routers, and software. The company's offerings include:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Industrial Asset Vision</strong>: An all-in-one cloud-based LoRaWAN solution integrating Cisco sensors, gateways, and network servers for seamless deployment.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Customizable Enterprise Solutions</strong>: Cisco collaborates with Actility and WMW to offer flexible deployments for sensitive use cases, including on-premises Docker-based configurations for government applications.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p><strong>Solving Data Sovereignty and Security Challenges</strong><br>
<!-- -->In the U.S., government data must comply with strict sovereignty and security regulations, often necessitating that all data remain within national borders. Cisco addresses these requirements by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Deploying Docker containers for network and application servers on government-approved private clouds like AWS GovCloud and Microsoft Azure for secure, localized data processing.</li>
<li>Ensuring the solutions meet certifications up to top-secret classification.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>LoRaWAN in Military Aviation</strong><br>
<!-- -->Cisco's solutions are being implemented in U.S. military aviation to digitize processes and improve operational readiness. Key insights include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aircraft Readiness Challenges</strong>: The U.S. military aims for 80% aircraft readiness, but current rates are well below that for both legacy (F-22) and modern (F-35) fighter jets. LoRaWAN technology helps streamline maintenance and resource allocation.</li>
<li><strong>Fuel Truck Monitoring</strong>: Previously reliant on manual measurements with sticks, jet fuel levels are now digitized with LoRaWAN sensors, ensuring accurate data and reducing errors.</li>
<li><strong>Asset Tracking</strong>: From nitrogen carts to fuel trucks, LoRaWAN devices help locate critical resources and prevent logistical disputes between branches like the Navy and Marines.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Improving Safety and Efficiency</strong><br>
<!-- -->LoRaWAN is also being used to enhance safety and situational awareness:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tracking Personnel</strong>: Sensors help locate personnel in challenging conditions, such as Marines operating in low visibility.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring Equipment</strong>: Vehicles, doors, and other assets are being digitized to ensure they are always accounted for.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Why LoRaWAN is Effective for Government Use Cases</strong><br>
<!-- -->Cisco's LoRaWAN deployments for the U.S. government underscore the technology's adaptability and scalability. Its ability to operate on-premises, comply with stringent security standards, and integrate with existing infrastructure makes it an ideal choice for mission-critical applications.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Takeaways</strong><br>
<!-- -->By digitizing processes and providing secure, localized solutions, LoRaWAN is enhancing military readiness, safety, and resource management. As adoption continues to grow, its role in ensuring mission-critical efficiency will only expand.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Nik Hawks</name>
            <uri>https://meteoscientific.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="lorawan" term="lorawan"/>
        <category label="government" term="government"/>
        <category label="military" term="military"/>
        <category label="aviation" term="aviation"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maximizing Efficiency and Safety with LoRaWAN - A New Edge for Commercial Building Framing]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/12/01/Using_LoRaWAN_For_Commercial_Building_Framing</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/12/01/Using_LoRaWAN_For_Commercial_Building_Framing"/>
        <updated>2023-12-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the foreman in charge of framing jobs on commercial buildings, you’re tasked with ensuring efficiency, profitability, and safety. These responsibilities can feel burdensome, but integrating LoRaWAN technology into your operations could be the game-changing solution you need. This low-power, long-range wireless protocol is reshaping the construction industry, providing ways to cut costs, boost revenue, and enhance safety measures.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As the foreman in charge of framing jobs on commercial buildings, you’re tasked with ensuring efficiency, profitability, and safety. These responsibilities can feel burdensome, but integrating LoRaWAN technology into your operations could be the game-changing solution you need. This low-power, long-range wireless protocol is reshaping the construction industry, providing ways to cut costs, boost revenue, and enhance safety measures.</p>
<p>Firstly, LoRaWAN can contribute significantly to cost-saving measures. By employing LoRaWAN-enabled sensors, you can monitor your equipment’s usage, state, and location. This data can help prevent tool loss and misuse, significantly reducing replacement or repair costs. Additionally, these sensors can identify maintenance needs before significant issues arise, averting costly downtime.</p>
<p>Besides saving money, LoRaWAN can also open new revenue streams. By offering clients the option of LoRaWAN-based monitoring systems, you provide value-added services such as real-time progress tracking and early detection of potential structural issues. This technological integration differentiates your service from competitors, potentially attracting more business and commanding higher rates for your advanced capabilities.</p>
<p>LoRaWAN’s benefits also extend to improving on-site safety, a critical aspect in the commercial building industry. For instance, the technology can be utilized to monitor structural stability during the framing process, alerting you to any potential risks before they escalate. Sensors can also track environmental conditions like temperature and humidity, alerting the team to unfavorable working conditions.</p>
<p>Additionally, the application of wearable LoRaWAN devices can play a pivotal role in reducing injuries. These devices can monitor workers’ vitals, fatigue levels, or detect falls, ensuring quick response to any health and safety threats. An added benefit is that these measures can help reduce insurance premiums by demonstrating commitment to worker safety.</p>
<p>Integrating LoRaWAN technology into your framing operations presents multiple benefits, from cost savings to revenue generation and safety enhancement. As a foreman, you’re always seeking ways to optimize your operations without compromising on quality or safety. Adopting LoRaWAN might be the key to achieving these goals while ensuring that your crew and business are future-ready.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="trades" term="trades"/>
        <category label="framing" term="framing"/>
        <category label="sensors" term="sensors"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating LoRaWAN Technology - A Transition Strategy for Seasoned Electricians]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/11/15/LoRaWAN_for_Electricians</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/11/15/LoRaWAN_for_Electricians"/>
        <updated>2023-11-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Navigating the increasingly digitized world of the trades can seem daunting, especially for established professionals considering retirement. It’s not uncommon for seasoned electricians to view the influx of new technology, such as the LoRaWAN protocol, as a disruptor rather than an opportunity. However, leveraging LoRaWAN could be a compelling selling point when transitioning your business to a younger generation, maximizing its value and ensuring its longevity in the hands of a new owner.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Navigating the increasingly digitized world of the trades can seem daunting, especially for established professionals considering retirement. It’s not uncommon for seasoned electricians to view the influx of new technology, such as the LoRaWAN protocol, as a disruptor rather than an opportunity. However, leveraging LoRaWAN could be a compelling selling point when transitioning your business to a younger generation, maximizing its value and ensuring its longevity in the hands of a new owner.</p>
<p>Firstly, implementing LoRaWAN technology now will future-proof your business, making it an attractive investment for a younger, tech-savvy electrician. The use of LoRaWAN-enabled sensors in electrical installations, for instance, can streamline maintenance and prevent potential faults. Sensors can monitor system performance, energy usage, or even predict possible equipment failures. The business that can offer such proactive services will stand out in a competitive market, increasing its appeal to prospective buyers.</p>
<p>In addition, the operational efficiency facilitated by LoRaWAN is a powerful asset when selling your business. The protocol allows for real-time asset tracking, optimizing the use of tools, equipment, and vehicles, reducing overhead costs. If you can show a potential buyer that your business operates smoothly with minimized costs, the perceived value of your enterprise increases.</p>
<p>Moreover, incorporating LoRaWAN into your business model opens up potential new revenue streams that can make your enterprise more appealing to a younger buyer. By offering smart, sensor-enabled electrical systems to your customers, you’re not only delivering a modern solution but also paving the way for recurring revenue. These systems usually require ongoing maintenance and updates, securing future income for the business.</p>
<p>Beyond this, demonstrating a commitment to environmental responsibility through the use of LoRaWAN technology can also enhance your business’s value. By facilitating energy efficiency and monitoring, these systems support green initiatives. Younger electricians, like their clients, are often conscious of sustainability, and a business that aligns with this ethos is likely to be more appealing.</p>
<p>Integrating LoRaWAN technology into your business operations can significantly enhance the attractiveness and value of your enterprise to a potential buyer. As an established electrician contemplating retirement, embracing this technology can ease the transition, help you sell your business at a premium, and ensure its future success in the hands of a new owner. By adapting to the evolving technological landscape, you’re not only securing your legacy but also paving the way for the next generation in the trade.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="electrician" term="electrician"/>
        <category label="trades" term="trades"/>
        <category label="sensors" term="sensors"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enhancing Revenue with LoRaWAN - An Innovative Approach for Plumbing Businesses]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/11/01/Enhancing_Revenue_With_LoRaWAN</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/11/01/Enhancing_Revenue_With_LoRaWAN"/>
        <updated>2023-11-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In an ever-evolving technological landscape, businesses must adapt to stay ahead. One such technology that is revolutionizing how industries operate is LoRaWAN, a long-range, low-power wide-area networking (LPWAN) protocol. It’s helping various sectors improve efficiency and reduce costs, and the plumbing industry is no exception. With the potential to transform how plumbers work, LoRaWAN can facilitate faster service, better customer satisfaction, and ultimately, an increase in revenue.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In an ever-evolving technological landscape, businesses must adapt to stay ahead. One such technology that is revolutionizing how industries operate is LoRaWAN, a long-range, low-power wide-area networking (LPWAN) protocol. It’s helping various sectors improve efficiency and reduce costs, and the plumbing industry is no exception. With the potential to transform how plumbers work, LoRaWAN can facilitate faster service, better customer satisfaction, and ultimately, an increase in revenue.</p>
<p>Firstly, by implementing LoRaWAN-enabled sensors in customers’ plumbing systems, plumbers can offer proactive maintenance services. These sensors can detect potential problems such as water pressure inconsistencies, leaks, and pipe blockages even before they cause serious damage.</p>
<p>When the system identifies an issue, it sends an alert to the plumbing company, allowing for swift action. This approach prevents extensive damage that often results in expensive repairs, thereby saving the customer money. Happy customers are more likely to return for services and recommend the business to others, enhancing the company’s revenue.</p>
<p>Additionally, LoRaWAN can help plumbers better manage their resources and reduce operational costs. For instance, by using LoRaWAN-enabled GPS trackers on plumbing vans, businesses can improve their dispatch efficiency and optimize routes, saving both time and fuel costs. Companies can also monitor equipment usage and identify which tools are used most often. This data enables businesses to make informed decisions about equipment investment, reducing unnecessary spending and maximizing ROI.</p>
<p>Moreover, introducing LoRaWAN in the plumbing business can also lead to new, untapped revenue streams. Offering customers the option to install smart, sensor-enabled plumbing systems could be a significant upsell opportunity. By providing these high-tech solutions, plumbers not only serve their customers better but also position themselves as industry leaders in technological innovation. This positioning could attract more customers and encourage existing ones to opt for higher-priced services.</p>
<p>Finally, LoRaWAN’s benefits extend to environmental responsibility—a selling point for many modern customers. By identifying leaks and inefficiencies, these smart systems can significantly reduce water waste, contributing to conservation efforts. Many customers are willing to pay a premium for services from environmentally responsible companies, which can directly increase revenue.</p>
<p>In conclusion, by leveraging LoRaWAN, plumbing businesses can enhance their services, improve operational efficiency, tap into new revenue streams, and appeal to eco-conscious consumers. By embracing this technological advancement, plumbing companies can stay at the forefront of their industry, keeping customers satisfied and boosting their bottom line.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="sensors" term="sensors"/>
        <category label="plumbing" term="plumbing"/>
        <category label="trades" term="trades"/>
        <category label="LoRaWAN" term="LoRaWAN"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using LoRaWAN to Monitor Water Levels in Vernal Pools]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/10/15/Using_LoRaWAN_Monitor_Water_Levels_in_Vernal_Pools</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/10/15/Using_LoRaWAN_Monitor_Water_Levels_in_Vernal_Pools"/>
        <updated>2023-10-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vernal pools are unique bodies of water that are of great ecological importance, but are often difficult to monitor and study due to their remote locations. LoRaWAN technology, a low-power, wide-area network communication system, presents a valuable solution to this challenge.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Vernal pools are unique bodies of water that are of great ecological importance, but are often difficult to monitor and study due to their remote locations. LoRaWAN technology, a low-power, wide-area network communication system, presents a valuable solution to this challenge.</p>
<p>A vernal pool is a temporary body of water that typically forms in the spring and dries up in the summer. These pools are home to a variety of plants and animals that are adapted to survive in these unique habitats, many of which are found nowhere else in the world. Vernal pools are considered keystone habitats and are critical to the survival of many threatened and endangered species.</p>
<p>Tracking the water levels of vernal pools is important for understanding how these pools are changing over time and what impact this might have on the plants and animals that live there. It also helps in managing these pools for human use and understanding how climate change is affecting these pools. However, monitoring vernal pools can be challenging due to their remote and inaccessible locations.</p>
<p>This is where LoRaWAN technology comes in. LoRaWAN is a low-power, wide-area network communication system that allows for remote monitoring of water levels in vernal pools. The system uses sensors to collect data on water levels, which is then transmitted wirelessly to a central location for analysis. The sensors are small, low-power, and long-range, making them ideal for use in remote locations.</p>
<p>In San Diego, conditions are particularly favorable for using LoRaWAN to monitor water levels in our chaparral vernal pools. These pools are located in a semi-arid chaparral ecosystem, which means that they are often subject to prolonged dry periods. This makes it crucial to have accurate water level data in order to understand how these pools are changing over time and how they are being impacted by climate change. Additionally, chaparral vernal pools are also home to several threatened and endangered species, making the monitoring and preservation of these pools particularly important.</p>
<p>LoRaWAN technology presents a valuable solution to the challenge of monitoring remote vernal pools. The technology allows for accurate and reliable data collection in remote locations, which is crucial for understanding how these pools are changing over time and for managing and preserving these unique habitats and the species that depend on them. In San Diego, the conditions are particularly favorable for using LoRaWAN to monitor chaparral vernal pools, and this technology has the potential to play a key role in the conservation and management of these pools in the future.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="applied micrometeorology" term="applied micrometeorology"/>
        <category label="environmental science" term="environmental science"/>
        <category label="LoRaWAN" term="LoRaWAN"/>
        <category label="vernal pools" term="vernal pools"/>
        <category label="water measurement" term="water measurement"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Measurements in Micrometeorology]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/10/02/Measurements-in-Micrometeorology</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/10/02/Measurements-in-Micrometeorology"/>
        <updated>2023-10-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the most important aspects of micrometeorology is the use of measurements to understand and predict how these processes will change over time.  Here are the 8 measurements you'll need to know.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most important aspects of micrometeorology is the use of measurements to understand and predict how these processes will change over time.  Here are the 8 measurements you'll need to know. </p>
<p><strong>Temperature:</strong> Temperature is a measure of how hot or cold something is. In micrometeorology, temperature measurements are used to understand how heat is transferred between the air and the ground, and how this affects the local climate. Temperature measurements are usually taken using thermometers, which can be placed in the air or on the ground to measure the temperature at different heights and locations.</p>
<p><strong>Humidity:</strong> Humidity is a measure of the amount of water vapor in the air. In micrometeorology, humidity measurements are used to understand how water is transferred between the air and the ground, and how this affects the local climate. Humidity measurements are usually taken using hygrometers, which can be placed in the air or on the ground to measure the humidity at different heights and locations.</p>
<p><strong>Wind speed and direction:</strong> Wind is the movement of air across the surface of the Earth. In micrometeorology, wind speed and direction measurements are used to understand how air is moved around by the wind, and how this affects the local climate. Wind speed and direction measurements are usually taken using anemometers and wind vanes, which can be placed in the air or on the ground to measure the wind at different heights and locations.</p>
<p><strong>Precipitation:</strong> Precipitation is any form of water that falls from the sky, such as rain, snow, or sleet. In micrometeorology, precipitation measurements are used to understand how water is transferred between the air and the ground, and how this affects the local climate. Precipitation measurements are usually taken using rain gauges, which can be placed on the ground to measure the amount of precipitation that falls in a particular location.</p>
<p><strong>Solar radiation:</strong> Solar radiation is the energy that is emitted by the sun. In micrometeorology, solar radiation measurements are used to understand how the sun’s energy is absorbed and reflected by the Earth’s surface, and how this affects the local climate. Solar radiation measurements are usually taken using pyranometers, which can be placed in the air or on the ground to measure the amount of solar radiation that is received at different heights and locations.</p>
<p><strong>Evaporation:</strong> Evaporation is the process by which water is converted into water vapor and released into the air. In micrometeorology, evaporation measurements are used to understand how water is transferred between the air and the ground, and how this affects the local climate. Evaporation measurements are usually taken using lysimeters, which can be placed on the ground to measure the amount of water that is lost through evaporation in a particular location.</p>
<p><strong>Soil moisture:</strong> Soil moisture is the amount of water that is contained in the soil. In micrometeorology, soil moisture measurements are used to understand how water is transferred between the air and the ground, and how this affects the local climate. Soil moisture measurements are usually taken using soil moisture probes, which can be placed in the soil to measure the moisture content at different depths and locations.</p>
<p>These 8 measurements are at the core of what micrometeorology relies on to understand and predict small-scale weather</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="weather" term="weather"/>
        <category label="sensors" term="sensors"/>
        <category label="agriculture" term="agriculture"/>
        <category label="environmental science" term="environmental science"/>
        <category label="micrometeorological concepts" term="micrometeorological concepts"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why You Want A High Meteorological Sensor Density]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/09/15/High-Meteorological-Sensor-Density</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/09/15/High-Meteorological-Sensor-Density"/>
        <updated>2023-09-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a farmer or land owner, it is important to have accurate and reliable information about the weather and climate conditions on your property. This can help you to make informed decisions about things like when to plant and harvest crops, how to manage your land and resources, and how to prepare for extreme weather events.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a farmer or land owner, it is important to have accurate and reliable information about the weather and climate conditions on your property. This can help you to make informed decisions about things like when to plant and harvest crops, how to manage your land and resources, and how to prepare for extreme weather events.</p>
<p>One way to get this information is by using meteorological sensors to measure weather and climate data on your property. These sensors can provide detailed and accurate information about factors like temperature, humidity, wind speed, and precipitation, which can help you to better understand the conditions on your land and how they are changing over time.</p>
<p>However, the density of these sensors is also important. A high density of meteorological sensors on your property means that you will have more data to work with, which can provide a more complete and accurate picture of the weather and climate conditions on your land. This can be especially useful if you have a large property with a varied landscape, as it can help you to understand the different microclimates and how they are affecting your crops and other resources.</p>
<p>In addition, having a high density of meteorological sensors on your property can also be beneficial for the broader community. By collecting and sharing this data, you can help to improve our understanding of the weather and climate patterns in your area and how they are changing over time. This can help to inform decision making at the local, regional, and even global level, and can help to protect the environment and human health.</p>
<p>Overall, there are many good reasons why every farmer and land owner should want a high meteorological sensor density on their property. By using these sensors to gather accurate and reliable weather and climate data, you can make better informed decisions about your land and resources, and contribute to a greater understanding of the weather and climate patterns in your area.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="weather" term="weather"/>
        <category label="sensor density" term="sensor density"/>
        <category label="agriculture" term="agriculture"/>
        <category label="soil sensors" term="soil sensors"/>
        <category label="temperature sensors" term="temperature sensors"/>
        <category label="microcmeteorological concepts" term="microcmeteorological concepts"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Soil, Air, and Atmospheric Stability]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/09/01/Soil-Air-Atmospheric-Stability</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/09/01/Soil-Air-Atmospheric-Stability"/>
        <updated>2023-09-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The delta between soil and air temperatures can give us clues about the stability of the atmosphere. When the soil is much warmer than the air, it can indicate that the air is likely to rise quickly. This rising air is known as convection, and it can lead to the formation of clouds and storms. On the other hand, if the soil is much cooler than the air, it can indicate that the air will sink, which can lead to calm and stable weather.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The delta between soil and air temperatures can give us clues about the stability of the atmosphere. When the soil is much warmer than the air, it can indicate that the air is likely to rise quickly. This rising air is known as convection, and it can lead to the formation of clouds and storms. On the other hand, if the soil is much cooler than the air, it can indicate that the air will sink, which can lead to calm and stable weather.</p>
<p>The rate at which the air temperature changes with altitude is called the “lapse rate.” The lapse rate is an important factor in determining the stability of the atmosphere. If the lapse rate is high, it means that the temperature is changing quickly with altitude. This can lead to unstable conditions, as the temperature difference between the warm air near the surface and the colder air higher up creates an unstable environment for clouds and storms to form. On the other hand, if the lapse rate is low, it means that the temperature changes slowly with altitude, which can lead to more stable weather conditions.</p>
<p>An unstable atmosphere is one in which the air is prone to rising and falling quickly. This can lead to a variety of weather phenomena, including thunderstorms, clouds, and precipitation. Unstable atmospheric conditions can be caused by a number of factors, such as warm air at the surface, cold air aloft, and high lapse rates. On the other hand, a stable atmosphere is one in which the air is less likely to rise or fall quickly. This can lead to clear and calm weather conditions.</p>
<p>It’s important to pay attention to both soil and air temperatures, as well as the lapse rate, to get a better understanding of the current and future weather conditions. By understanding these differences, we can make better predictions and be better prepared for changes in the weather.</p>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<p>Lapse rate: <a href="https://www.britannica.com/science/lapse-rate" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.britannica.com/science/lapse-rate</a>
Unstable atmosphere: <a href="https://www.britannica.com/science/unstable-atmosphere" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.britannica.com/science/unstable-atmosphere</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="weather" term="weather"/>
        <category label="soil temperature" term="soil temperature"/>
        <category label="atmospheric" term="atmospheric"/>
        <category label="stability" term="stability"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[All About Valley Microclimates]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/08/15/All_About_Valley_Microclimates</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/08/15/All_About_Valley_Microclimates"/>
        <updated>2023-08-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A microclimate is the climate of a small, specific area, such as a valley. The microclimate of a valley can be different from the climate of the surrounding region, due to the way that the valley’s shape and other factors influence the movement of air and the amount of sunlight it receives.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A microclimate is the climate of a small, specific area, such as a valley. The microclimate of a valley can be different from the climate of the surrounding region, due to the way that the valley’s shape and other factors influence the movement of air and the amount of sunlight it receives.</p>
<p>At the valley floor, the microclimate may be warmer and more humid than at other levels, due to the way that the air is trapped within the valley and the presence of plants and other vegetation that can release moisture into the air.</p>
<p>Halfway up the mountain, the microclimate may be cooler and drier than at the valley floor, due to the higher elevation and the greater distance from the moist air near the ground. This can create a more pleasant climate for activities such as hiking or picnicking.</p>
<p>At the ridge top surrounding the valley, the microclimate may be even cooler and drier than at the halfway point, due to the even higher elevation and the exposure to the wind. This can create a challenging environment for plants and animals, and may require special adaptations in order to survive.</p>
<p>Overall, the microclimate of a valley can vary significantly at different levels, and these differences can have an impact on the plants, animals, and people that live in or visit the valley. Understanding these differences can help us to better understand and protect the unique ecosystems of valleys and other small areas.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="weather" term="weather"/>
        <category label="microclimates" term="microclimates"/>
        <category label="micrometeorology" term="micrometeorology"/>
        <category label="valley winds" term="valley winds"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Can A Daily Weather Sounding Tell Us?]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/08/01/Weather_Soundings</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/08/01/Weather_Soundings"/>
        <updated>2023-08-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A daily weather sounding is a measurement of the temperature, humidity, and wind speed in the atmosphere at different levels above the Earth’s surface. It is used to help predict the weather and to understand the processes that influence it.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A daily weather sounding is a measurement of the temperature, humidity, and wind speed in the atmosphere at different levels above the Earth’s surface. It is used to help predict the weather and to understand the processes that influence it.</p>
<p>To take a daily weather sounding, meteorologists use a weather balloon equipped with sensors that measure the temperature, humidity, and wind speed at different heights. The weather balloon is released into the atmosphere and rises up into the sky, transmitting the data it collects back to the ground as it goes.</p>
<p>The data collected by the weather balloon is used to create a daily weather sounding, which is a graph that shows how the temperature, humidity, and wind speed change at different heights above the Earth’s surface. By analyzing this data, meteorologists can get a better understanding of the weather patterns and how they are likely to change in the coming days.</p>
<p>For example, a daily weather sounding can help meteorologists to identify areas of high and low pressure in the atmosphere and to predict the likelihood of rain or other precipitation. It can also help them to understand the movements of warm and cold air masses, which can influence the temperature and weather patterns in different parts of the world.</p>
<p>Overall, a daily weather sounding is an important tool for predicting the weather and understanding the processes that influence it. By analyzing the data collected by weather balloons, meteorologists can provide accurate and reliable forecasts to help people plan their activities and stay safe.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="weather" term="weather"/>
        <category label="weather sounding" term="weather sounding"/>
        <category label="environmental science" term="environmental science"/>
        <category label="micrometeorology" term="micrometeorology"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Applications of Micrometeorology]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/07/15/Applications-of-Micrometeorology</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/07/15/Applications-of-Micrometeorology"/>
        <updated>2023-07-15T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Micrometeorology is an important field that helps us to understand how small-scale weather and climate processes will affect things like agriculture, forestry, and the natural environment. Let’s take a closer look at some of the various applications of micrometeorology in different fields.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Micrometeorology is an important field that helps us to understand how small-scale weather and climate processes will affect things like agriculture, forestry, and the natural environment. Let’s take a closer look at some of the various applications of micrometeorology in different fields.</p>
<p>One area where micrometeorology is particularly important is agriculture. Farmers rely on the weather and climate to grow their crops, and understanding how these things will change over time can help them to make better decisions about when to plant and harvest their crops. For example, if a farmer knows that there is a high probability of drought in the coming months, they may decide to plant drought-resistant crops to increase their chances of success.</p>
<p>Micrometeorology is also important in the field of environmental science. By studying the small-scale weather and climate processes that occur close to the Earth’s surface, scientists can better understand how these processes contribute to larger-scale climate changes, such as global warming. This information can help us to develop strategies for reducing our carbon emissions and mitigating the impact of climate change.</p>
<p>Finally, micrometeorology is also used in military contexts to help with things like weather forecasting and mission planning. For example, the military may use micrometeorology data to predict the weather conditions that troops will encounter in a particular area, and to plan their missions accordingly.</p>
<p>Micrometeorology is a vital field of study that has many practical applications in a variety of fields. By understanding the small-scale weather and climate processes that occur close to the Earth’s surface, we can make better decisions about things like agriculture, environmental management, and military operations.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="weather" term="weather"/>
        <category label="air pollution" term="air pollution"/>
        <category label="micrometeorology" term="micrometeorology"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding PM 2.5 and PM 10 Levels]]></title>
        <id>https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/07/01/PM_Levels</id>
        <link href="https://www.meteoscientific.com/blog/2023/07/01/PM_Levels"/>
        <updated>2023-07-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[PM 2.5 and PM 10 are two types of air pollution that can have harmful effects on human health. PM stands for “particulate matter,” and the numbers refer to the size of the particles in micrometers.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>PM 2.5 and PM 10 are two types of air pollution that can have harmful effects on human health. PM stands for “particulate matter,” and the numbers refer to the size of the particles in micrometers.</p>
<p>PM 2.5 particles are very small, with a diameter of 2.5 micrometers or less, while PM 10 particles are slightly larger, with a diameter of 10 micrometers or less.</p>
<p>Both PM 2.5 and PM 10 particles can come from a variety of sources, including car and truck emissions, power plants, construction sites, and fires. These particles can be inhaled into the lungs and cause respiratory problems, such as asthma and bronchitis. They can also contribute to heart disease and other health problems.</p>
<p>High levels of PM 2.5 and PM 10 pollution can be particularly harmful to people who are already at risk of respiratory problems, such as children, older adults, and people with asthma or other lung conditions. High levels of either type of pollution can also have wider impacts, such as reducing visibility and damaging crops and other vegetation.</p>
<p>To protect human health and the environment, it is important to reduce the levels of PM 2.5 and PM 10 pollution in the air. This can be done by controlling emissions from cars, power plants, and other sources, and by promoting the use of clean energy technologies. By taking these steps, we can help to improve the air quality and protect the health of people around the world.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>MeteoScientific</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/meteoscientific/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="weather" term="weather"/>
        <category label="particulates" term="particulates"/>
        <category label="air pollution" term="air pollution"/>
    </entry>
</feed>